<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/max/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-04-22T23:15:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/max/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">UBI Center | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Analyzing universal basic income policies with open-source research</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">California’s basic income bill still needs work</title>
      <link href="/california-ab65-calubi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="California's basic income bill still needs work" />
      <published>2021-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/california-ab65-calubi</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/california-ab65-calubi">&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the California Democratic Party &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/12/california-democratic-party-platform-supports-universal-basic-income.html&quot;&gt;added&lt;/a&gt; Universal Basic Income (UBI) to their party platform. Two years later, Assemblymember Evan Low (D-Campbell), who served as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ebar.com/news/latest_news//286838&quot;&gt;national co-chair&lt;/a&gt; for Andrew Yang’s presidential campaign, introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201920200AB2712&quot;&gt;UBI bill&lt;/a&gt; for California. In December 2020, Low reintroduced the bill for the 2020-21 legislative session, this time with Senator Scott Wiener (D-San Francisco) as a coauthor and adding some minor revisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That bill, &lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=202120220AB65&quot;&gt;AB65&lt;/a&gt;, establishes the CalUBI program to provide $1,000 per month to most California adults. We estimate that CalUBI would cut poverty by 83% while adding $282 billion to the annual state deficit. In this article, we provide more detail into these estimates and suggest paths toward feasible legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;californias-extreme-economy&quot;&gt;California’s extreme economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;California is both rich and poor. It ranks #8 among US states on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_U.S._states_and_territories_by_GDP_per_capita&quot;&gt;GDP per capita&lt;/a&gt;, and #7 on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_U.S._states_and_territories_by_income&quot;&gt;median household income&lt;/a&gt;. It also ranks &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/multimedia/unequal-states-of-america/#/California&quot;&gt;#7 on income inequality&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and accordingly, its poverty rate is higher than its GDP would predict, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_U.S._states_and_territories_by_poverty_rate#cite_note-9&quot;&gt;ranking #25&lt;/a&gt; based on the Official Poverty Measure (OPM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using the Supplemental Poverty Measure&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (SPM), however, California ranks &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/content/dam/Census/library/publications/2020/demo/p60-272.pdf&quot;&gt;#1 on both overall poverty and child poverty&lt;/a&gt;: 17.2% of Californians are in poverty, compared to 12.5% of Americans. In fact, California has ranked #1 on SPM poverty every year since the Census Bureau first reported it by state in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.census.gov/library/publications/2012/demo/p60-244.pdf&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;. That’s because the SPM, unlike the OPM, adjusts for taxes, in-kind benefits (like the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program), and, most importantly for California, local housing costs. As a result of its housing shortage (California has the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MaxGhenis/status/1187898060409466882&quot;&gt;fewest housing units per adult&lt;/a&gt; of any state), housing in California is notoriously expensive—&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldpopulationreview.com/state-rankings/cost-of-living-index-by-state&quot;&gt;second only to Hawaii&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;California also stands out in terms of taxation.
Due to Prop 13 (1978), a ballot measure that limits property taxes, it ranks &lt;a href=&quot;https://wallethub.com/edu/states-with-the-highest-and-lowest-property-taxes/11585&quot;&gt;#35 on local property taxes&lt;/a&gt;.
The state offsets that revenue loss with high income taxes—its &lt;a href=&quot;https://taxfoundation.org/publications/state-individual-income-tax-rates-and-brackets/&quot;&gt;top marginal rate is 13.3%&lt;/a&gt;, the highest of any state—and high sales taxes—its &lt;a href=&quot;https://taxfoundation.org/2020-sales-taxes/&quot;&gt;state rate is 7.25%&lt;/a&gt;, the highest of any state, and its state and local combined rate ranks #9. It is among the 41 states that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbpp.org/research/state-budget-and-tax/state-taxes-on-capital-gains&quot;&gt;tax capital gains as ordinary income&lt;/a&gt;, which raises significant revenue given its residents claim 8.1% of their income in capital gains, a higher share than all but three states. The net result is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://taxfoundation.org/publications/state-local-tax-burden-rankings/&quot;&gt;state and local tax burden of 11.5%&lt;/a&gt;, ranking #8 across states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state deploys these higher-than-average tax revenues for generous transfers. It matches the federal Earned Income Tax Credit at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urban.org/policy-centers/cross-center-initiatives/state-and-local-finance-initiative/state-and-local-backgrounders/state-earned-income-tax-credits&quot;&gt;85% for low income workers&lt;/a&gt;, a higher rate than any other state, and adds a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ftb.ca.gov/file/personal/credits/california-earned-income-tax-credit.html&quot;&gt;Young Child Tax Credit&lt;/a&gt; supplement for qualifying families with children under age 6. Due to generously funding the Aid to Dependent Families Children (cash welfare) matching grant in the 1990s, California today gets &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.niskanencenter.org/inequitable-and-inadequate-reforming-federal-grants-for-state-social-assistance-programs/&quot;&gt;more per child&lt;/a&gt; from its replacement, Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF), than all states but New York and Vermont. And while California has &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.db101.org/ca/programs/income_support/calworks/program2.htm&quot;&gt;not yet eliminated asset limits for TANF&lt;/a&gt;, it is among the 33 states to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbpp.org/research/food-assistance/snaps-broad-based-categorical-eligibility-supports-working-families-and&quot;&gt;raised income and asset limits for SNAP&lt;/a&gt;. It &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue-brief/status-of-state-medicaid-expansion-decisions-interactive-map/&quot;&gt;expanded Medicaid&lt;/a&gt; as quickly as it could following the passage of the Affordable Care Act, and overall spends more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taxpolicycenter.org/statistics/state-and-local-general-expenditures-capita&quot;&gt;per capita on public welfare&lt;/a&gt; than 43 states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of welfare spending doesn’t explain California’s highest-in-the-nation poverty rate, but more inclusive and generous welfare programs can nonetheless ameliorate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-impact-of-ab65&quot;&gt;The impact of AB65&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AB65 creates the CalUBI program, which provides $1,000 per month to Californians meeting these eligibility conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(A) Is a resident, and has been a resident for the three most recent consecutive taxable years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(B) Is at least 18 years of age.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(C) Is not currently incarcerated in a county jail or the state prison.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(D) Reported gross income that does not exceed 200 percent of the median per capita income for the eligible recipient’s current county of residence, as determined by the United States Census Bureau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AB65 also levies a 1% tax on incomes above $2 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using data from the 2017-2019 Current Population Survey March Supplements, we estimate that 58% of Californians would be eligible for CalUBI. 77% meet the age requirement, 83% meet the income requirement,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 97% meet the migration requirement,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and 99.5% meet the incarceration requirement.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Providing the $12,000 payment to each of the 23.6 million eligible recipients would cost $283 billion per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enacting the policy would reduce poverty by 83%, to 3.0%; for context, Minnesota currently has the lowest poverty rate, at 6.5%. It would also reduce inequality by 26%.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For these calculations, we assume that the CalUBI would not be counted as income for tax liabilities or benefit eligibility, though this may be unrealistic: Alaska’s Permanent Fund Dividend does not affect eligibility for programs like &lt;a href=&quot;https://ak.db101.org/ak/programs/income_support/ssi/faqs.htm#_q7329&quot;&gt;Supplemental Security Income&lt;/a&gt;, but the payments are &lt;a href=&quot;https://pfd.alaska.gov/Payments/Tax-Information#:~:text=Even%20if%20part%20or%20all,Permanent%20Fund%20Dividend%20is%20%24992.00.&quot;&gt;subject&lt;/a&gt; to federal income tax (Alaska has &lt;a href=&quot;http://tax.alaska.gov/programs/programs/index.aspx?10001&quot;&gt;no state income tax&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the program lacks funding. Using the Policy Simulation Library’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.compute.studio/PSLmodels/Tax-Brain/&quot;&gt;TaxBrain&lt;/a&gt; tool and the IRS Public Use File, we estimate that a 1% tax on incomes above $2 million would raise &lt;a href=&quot;https://compute.studio/PSLmodels/Tax-Brain/50389/&quot;&gt;$2.33 billion federally&lt;/a&gt;. Scaling that down to California by its share of personal income in excess of $100,000&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; yields a revenue estimate of $340 million, or 0.1% of CalUBI’s cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;perverse-incentives-from-means-testing&quot;&gt;Perverse incentives from means-testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CalUBI means-testing approach creates perverse incentives in two ways: its immediate benefit cliff discourages people from working, and its geographic cliff discourages people from residing in lower-income counties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, consider a single resident of Santa Clara County earning $100,000 per year, let’s call them Alex. Santa Clara County is home to Google, Apple, San Jose, and Assemblymember Evan Low, and its median personal income is about $53,500, second only to San Francisco County ($55,000) in California. With income below twice the median, Alex would be eligible for CalUBI. Their net income would be $100,000 minus $28,743 in federal, FICA, and state income taxes,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; plus $12,000 in CalUBI, totaling $83,257.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now suppose Alex is offered a job that pays 10% more. At $110,000 income, they exceed the $107,000 CalUBI threshold for Santa Clara County, so they no longer receive the $12,000 payment. As a result of their raise, Alex’s net income &lt;em&gt;falls 7%&lt;/em&gt; from $83,257 to $77,162. To get back to their original net income, they’d have to earn more than $120,000; if Alex can’t get at least a 20% raise, they’re better off with their current income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose that instead of taking a new higher-paying job in Santa Clara County, Alex considers moving to neighboring Santa Cruz County for a job paying the same $100,000. Where the median income in Santa Clara County is over $53,000, it’s under $33,000 in Santa Cruz County. Alex would lose CalUBI eligibility, and their net income would therefore fall $12,000—a full 14%—if they were to cross the county border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These welfare cliffs and discontinuities harmfully distort behavior. People like Alex will avoid earning too much money, or perhaps they’ll favor a job with deferred compensation plans to lower their income, or they’ll defer capital gains themselves, all to stay under the threshold in their county. They’ll also avoid moving to lower-income areas, maybe choosing to commute from a more expensive area instead to retain CalUBI eligibility. This would increase geographic inequalities by raising high-income people’s demand to live in high-income areas. Just as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0094119011000520&quot;&gt;school district boundaries determine housing prices&lt;/a&gt;, county boundaries would do the same under this policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;universal-designs&quot;&gt;Universal designs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AB65’s cliff could be mitigated by phasing the benefit out with income, as programs like SNAP and the Earned Income Tax Credit do, and as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Negative_income_tax&quot;&gt;negative income tax&lt;/a&gt; cousin of UBI does. Depending on the design, this could avoid Alex’s quagmire and ensure that any additional dollar they earn raises their net income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this phase-out would be a hidden tax: if the benefit phases out at 50 cents per dollar of earnings, that’s equivalent to a 50% marginal tax, on top of normal taxes and phase-outs of other benefits. The array of means-tested benefits explains why parents around the poverty line currently face &lt;a href=&quot;https://aspe.hhs.gov/system/files/aspe-files/260661/brief2-overviewmtranalyses.pdf&quot;&gt;higher marginal tax rates&lt;/a&gt; than any other group in the country, often exceeding 50% and sometimes exceeding 100%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, if the benefit is means-tested but distributed monthly, recipients would be required to report changes to their income regularly. This costs recipients of existing benefits time and explains some of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbpp.org/research/romneys-charge-that-most-federal-low-income-spending-goes-for-overhead-and-bureaucrats-is&quot;&gt;high administrative overhead costs&lt;/a&gt;. To support income reporting requirements for the American Rescue Plan’s monthly Child Tax Credit expansion, the IRS is building a portal, an endeavor that’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://abc11.com/child-tax-credit-irs-stimulus-delay/10432494/&quot;&gt;slowing the delivery&lt;/a&gt; of funds to low and middle income parents. The alternative is how refundable tax credits work today: calculated from income often a year or more in the past, without the ability to meet real-time needs, especially when financial circumstances change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other AB65 targeting provisions have drawbacks, too. County-level income thresholds will induce migration even with phase-outs. A three-year residency requirement conflicts with Californians’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2021-04-01/skelton-ppic-poll-immigration-healthcare-california&quot;&gt;pro-immigration sentiment&lt;/a&gt; (the Alaska Permanent Fund Dividend only has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pfd.alaska.gov/Eligibility/Requirements&quot;&gt;one-year requirement&lt;/a&gt;). And as our other research shows, excluding children misses an opportunity to &lt;a href=&quot;https://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/empirical.html&quot;&gt;improve lifelong development&lt;/a&gt;, and to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20210120/child-ubi-share.html&quot;&gt;cost-effectively reduce poverty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universality bypasses all of these issues. Universal payments don’t discourage work through hidden taxes or cliffs; they don’t require recipients to report income more than once per tax year; they can be efficiently distributed; they demonstrate inclusiveness toward newcomers; and they provide kids the resources they need to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, universality is more expensive. Expanding CalUBI to each person in California would raise the cost from $283 billion to $472 billion—a sixth of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/CARGSP&quot;&gt;state’s GDP&lt;/a&gt; and more than twice the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.ca.gov/2021/01/08/governor-newsom-proposes-2021-22-state-budget&quot;&gt;current state budget&lt;/a&gt;. If funds could be conjured to pay for it, it would drive down the poverty rate to 1.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But given a fixed budget, poverty is often minimized by spreading it across more of the population in smaller amounts. Spreading the $283 billion across each person in California would give each about $590 per month, and this would have virtually the same antipoverty impact as the original proposal.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That is, excluding children and newcomers offsets the progressivity of excluding higher-income people (not to mention the distortions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the $283 billion price tag makes AB65 unworkable as written. What policies could make progress toward its goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-california-child-allowance&quot;&gt;A California child allowance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monthly cash transfers can efficiently relieve poverty and reduce inequality at the state level, but given to everyone, they’re costly. Even a $100 monthly UBI would cost California $48 billion per year, more than a fifth of the current state budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A focus on children could be a tenable, effective starting point. Given &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/CA&quot;&gt;9 million&lt;/a&gt; of California’s 40 million residents are under 18, a $100 monthly child allowance (cash payments given to parents for each child) would cost $11 billion annually. That’s 0.4% of &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/CARGSP&quot;&gt;California’s $2.9 trillion GDP&lt;/a&gt; or 5% of its proposed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebudget.ca.gov/2021-22/pdf/BudgetSummary/SummaryCharts.pdf&quot;&gt;$227 billion budget&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/simulation.html&quot;&gt;child allowance simulation&lt;/a&gt; shows that this would be achievable and impactful in California. The state could fund a $100 monthly child allowance with a 1% income tax, cutting child poverty by 16%, adult poverty by 5%, and overall poverty by 7%. The bottom decile of Californians would see incomes rise by 11%, and on average only the upper three deciles would lose income, and only by under 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/2021-04-03-california-ab65-calubi/deciles_100_child_allowance.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of revenue options could fund such a program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding to the income tax, as described in the above simulation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Applying California’s expected &lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/article/gavin-newsom-california-coronavirus-pandemic-8d01e88ceeb4b0bc6cb1fb0d6a8d72b7&quot;&gt;$15 billion surplus&lt;/a&gt; in 2021. This wouldn’t fund a permanent policy, but could fund a $100 monthly child allowance, plus a $100 monthly young child supplement, for a trial year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taxing commercial property at market value would raise between &lt;a href=&quot;https://lao.ca.gov/BallotAnalysis/Proposition?number=15&amp;amp;year=2020#:~:text=The%20measure%20requires%20commercial%20and,over%20time%20starting%20in%202022.&quot;&gt;$6.5 and $11.5 billion&lt;/a&gt; per year. A ballot measure to do this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2020-11-10/proposition-15-commercial-property-tax-defeated&quot;&gt;narrowly lost&lt;/a&gt; in 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ending the mortgage interest deduction on second homes would raise $250 million per year. &lt;a href=&quot;https://a25.asmdc.org/press-releases/20210219-assemblymember-alex-lee-introduces-repeal-regressive-mortgage-interest&quot;&gt;AB946&lt;/a&gt; proposes to do this, though the revenue is used for a first-time home buyer program.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conforming parts of the state income tax code with federal tax code changes enacted as part of the 2017 Tax Cuts and Jobs Act; this would raise &lt;a href=&quot;https://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3959&quot;&gt;$1.7 billion&lt;/a&gt; per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replacing other benefit programs, such as CalWORKS (the state TANF program), Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women, Infants, and Children (WIC), the child component of CalEITC, and the Young Child Tax Credit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instituting an estate tax, as was &lt;a href=&quot;https://sd11.senate.ca.gov/news/20190326-senator-wiener-introduces-california-estate-tax-proposal-fund-programs-reducing-wealth&quot;&gt;proposed in 2017&lt;/a&gt; and which was estimated to raise between $500 million and $1 billion per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repealing other state tax deductions that primarily benefit high income households, such as the property tax deduction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;or-a-california-young-child-allowance&quot;&gt;Or a California young child allowance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For greater affordability, California could focus on the group whose development is most sensitive to financial conditions, and whose needs are most costly due to childcare: young kids. Providing a young child allowance of $100 per month to each of California’s 3 million Californians children under age 6 would cost $4 billion annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Washington and Sacramento have both already prioritized the needs of young kids: the American Rescue Plan’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/up-front/2021/03/11/new-child-tax-credit-could-slash-poverty-now-and-boost-social-mobility-later/&quot;&gt;Child Tax Credit expansion&lt;/a&gt; provides an extra $50 per month to children under age 6 compared to older kids, and California provides a Young Child Tax Credit (YCTC) of up to $1,000 per year to families who qualify for the federal Earned Income Tax Credit and have at least one child under age 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transforming the YCTC into a young child allowance of $100 per month per child would have several benefits, by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Including families with no earned income who are ineligible for EITC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing more money for families with multiple young children&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoiding adding a 20% marginal tax to qualifying families with income between the phase-out region of $25,000 and $30,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Including children whose parents earn above $30,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhancing the benefit by at least $200 per year for all current recipients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meeting needs on a monthly basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potentially sending parents money proactively, rather than relying on families filing tax returns (many of whom don’t have to file since they don’t owe taxes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;california-can-make-policy-progress-toward-ubi&quot;&gt;California can make policy progress toward UBI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;California is in many ways the center of the UBI conversation. Its tech community has long promoted the idea as an insurance policy against technological unemployment, supporting Andrew Yang’s candidacy, funding basic income pilots, and donating to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/basic-income/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly’s basic income experiment&lt;/a&gt; in Kenya. Of the 40 mayors in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayorsforagi.org/&quot;&gt;Mayors for a Guaranteed Income&lt;/a&gt; network, 6 lead California cities, including its founder, Michael Tubbs. The pilot in Tubbs’s hometown of Stockton was one of the first of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/experiments-map/&quot;&gt;wave&lt;/a&gt; that now includes Compton, Long Beach, Oakland, Marin County, and San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These pilots may provide more precise estimates of how people respond to guaranteed income, but we already know from a slew of studies that cash transfers &lt;a href=&quot;https://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/empirical.html&quot;&gt;improve health, well-being, and educational outcomes&lt;/a&gt;, and that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/remahanna/files/151016_labor_supply_paper_draft_final.pdf&quot;&gt;don’t reduce labor supply much&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.worldbank.org/impactevaluations/do-poor-waste-transfers-booze-and-cigarettes-no&quot;&gt;raise spending on vices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In introducing AB65, Assemblymember Low has started the next phase of California’s UBI conversation. The idea is ready for policy implementation, but if it’s to be more than signaling, it will need to fit in a budget the governor can sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nick Rodelo provided research assistance for this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;California has the 7th highest ratio of top 1% to bottom 99% income: 30.7, compared to 26.3 nationwide. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Poverty researchers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2015/9/16/9337041/supplemental-poverty-measure&quot;&gt;generally prefer the SPM&lt;/a&gt; over the OPM, and that’s what the UBI Center uses in its analysis. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We interpreted a county’s “median per capita income” as the median personal income among people with income greater than zero. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Current Population Survey only includes migration data from one year ago. 1.0% of Californians lived in a different state one year ago. To approximate the three-year requirement, we tripled the observation weights for this 1%; this also served to “age” the data from the 2017-2019 period to 2021, as it produces a total population estimate of 40.1 million. The University of Virginia Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service &lt;a href=&quot;https://demographics.coopercenter.org/united-states-interactive-map&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; that California’s 2020 population was 40.4 million. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/cps/technical-documentation/methodology.html&quot;&gt;Current Population Survey omits prisoners&lt;/a&gt;, so we used data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prisonpolicy.org/profiles/CA.html&quot;&gt;Prison Policy Initiative&lt;/a&gt;, which estimates that 213,000 Californians were in state prison or county jail as of 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We measure inequality as the Gini index of the ratio between a person’s poverty unit’s (similar to a household) resources and its poverty threshold. The current value is 0.42, and under CalUBI it would fall to 0.31. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;High incomes in the Current Population Survey are obscured for privacy, such that only three records show personal income above $2 million. It estimates that Californians have a total of $321 billion of income in excess of $100,000, 15% of the $2.18 trillion of US personal income in excess of $100,000. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This and other calculations apply &lt;a href=&quot;https://smartasset.com/taxes/california-tax-calculator#VBrctYjFhi&quot;&gt;SmartAsset’s calculator&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;3.08% vs 3.03%. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="california" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">AB65 would cut poverty by 83%, but add $282 billion to the state deficit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UBI as a means of reducing gendered poverty</title>
      <link href="/womens-day-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UBI as a means of reducing gendered poverty" />
      <published>2021-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/womens-day-2021</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/womens-day-2021">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.internationalwomensday.com/&quot;&gt;International Women’s Day&lt;/a&gt; asks its celebrants to challenge the world in order to change it (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23ChooseToChallenge&quot;&gt;#ChooseToChallenge&lt;/a&gt;).
The following simulation seeks to challenge the fact that women in the United States are more likely to be impoverished than men.
In our analysis, we evaluate a Universal Basic Income (UBI), funded by a flat income tax, as a possible solution for both alleviating poverty and narrowing the gendered poverty gap.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:modeling&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:modeling&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poverty rates for children are roughly equal between genders, while adult women experience poverty at rates 17 percent greater than adult men: 12.4 percent vs. 10.6 percent.
As a general trend, the difference in poverty rates between women and men increases with age.
For example, 20.8 percent of women aged 85 or older are in poverty, compared to only 14.5 percent of men of the same age.
Among people aged 85 or older, women experience deep poverty at twice the rate of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import microdf as mdf
import numpy as np
import pandas as pd
import plotly.express as px
import ubicenter

df = pd.read_csv(
    &quot;https://github.com/MaxGhenis/datarepo/raw/master/pppub20.csv.gz&quot;,
    usecols=[
        &quot;MARSUPWT&quot;,
        &quot;SPM_RESOURCES&quot;,
        &quot;SPM_POVTHRESHOLD&quot;,
        &quot;SPM_WEIGHT&quot;,
        &quot;SPM_NUMPER&quot;,
        &quot;A_SEX&quot;,
        &quot;A_AGE&quot;,
        &quot;SPM_ID&quot;,
        &quot;AGI&quot;,
    ],
)
df.columns = df.columns.str.lower()
df[&quot;weight&quot;] = df.marsupwt / 100
df[&quot;spm_weight&quot;] = df.spm_weight / 100
df[&quot;female&quot;] = df.a_sex == 2
df[&quot;poverty&quot;] = df.spm_resources &amp;lt; df.spm_povthreshold
df[&quot;deep_poverty&quot;] = df.spm_resources &amp;lt; (df.spm_povthreshold / 2)
df[&quot;sex&quot;] = np.where(df.female, &quot;Female&quot;, &quot;Male&quot;)

spm = df.groupby(
    [&quot;spm_id&quot;, &quot;spm_resources&quot;, &quot;spm_weight&quot;, &quot;spm_povthreshold&quot;, &quot;spm_numper&quot;]
)[[&quot;agi&quot;]].sum()
spm[&quot;agi_pos&quot;] = np.maximum(spm.agi, 0)
spm.reset_index(inplace=True)

total_population = df.weight.sum()
total_agi_pos = mdf.weighted_sum(spm, &quot;agi_pos&quot;, &quot;spm_weight&quot;)

# Bin into ages aligning with 18 year old threshold.
DARK_PURPLE = &quot;#46296E&quot;  # Official Intl Womens Day Color.
LIGHT_PURPLE = &quot;#907EA8&quot;  # Lightened version.
DARK_GREY = &quot;#9E9E9E&quot;  # Gray 500 from Material Design.
LIGHT_GREY = &quot;#BDBDBD&quot;  # Gray 400.

COLOR_MAP = {
    &quot;Female&quot;: DARK_PURPLE,
    &quot;Male&quot;: LIGHT_GREY,
    &quot;Female poverty&quot;: DARK_PURPLE,
    &quot;Female deep poverty&quot;: LIGHT_PURPLE,
    &quot;Male poverty&quot;: DARK_GREY,
    &quot;Male deep poverty&quot;: LIGHT_GREY,
    &quot;Poverty&quot;: DARK_PURPLE,
    &quot;Deep poverty&quot;: LIGHT_PURPLE,
}

df[&quot;age_group&quot;] = pd.cut(df.a_age + 1, np.arange(0, 91, 5), labels=np.arange(0, 86, 5))
pov_age = mdf.weighted_mean(
    df, [&quot;poverty&quot;, &quot;deep_poverty&quot;], &quot;marsupwt&quot;, groupby=[&quot;age_group&quot;, &quot;sex&quot;]
)
pov_age = pov_age.round(3)
pov_age.reset_index(inplace=True)
pov_age = pov_age.melt([&quot;age_group&quot;, &quot;sex&quot;], [&quot;poverty&quot;, &quot;deep_poverty&quot;])
pov_age[&quot;label&quot;] = (
    pov_age.sex
    + &quot; &quot;
    + np.where(pov_age.variable == &quot;poverty&quot;, &quot;poverty&quot;, &quot;deep poverty&quot;)
)

fig = px.line(
    pov_age, x=&quot;age_group&quot;, y=&quot;value&quot;, color=&quot;label&quot;, color_discrete_map=COLOR_MAP
)
fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;Poverty by gender and age&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Age (in 5-year bins)&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;SPM poverty rate (2019)&quot;,
    legend_title=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickformat=&quot;%&quot;,
    yaxis_range=[0, pov_age.value.max() * 1.1] #fig.update_xaxes(range=[1.5, 4.5])
)

fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;, hovertemplate=None)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/womens-day-2021/2020-03-08-womens-day-2021-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
pov_age_diff = pov_age[pov_age.variable == &quot;poverty&quot;].pivot_table(
    values=&quot;value&quot;, index=&quot;age_group&quot;, columns=&quot;sex&quot;
)
pov_age_diff[&quot;female_minus_male&quot;] = pov_age_diff.Female - pov_age_diff.Male
pov_age_diff.female_minus_male.plot()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/womens-day-2021/2020-03-08-womens-day-2021-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a significant difference in rates of poverty for adult women as compared to men, how might a UBI help close that gap?
Our past modeling has shown that a UBI would lessen poverty across demographic groups, and also shrink poverty disparities by &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20210118/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021.html&quot;&gt;race&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201012/indigenous.html&quot;&gt;Indigenous heritage&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20200731/ada30.html&quot;&gt;disability status&lt;/a&gt;.
Our research here shows that it would do the same by gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After receiving a UBI, the poverty rates for women and men converge as the monthly amount increases (we’ve focused on adults here).
Consistent with our past simulations, a $300 monthly UBI would halve the rate of female poverty and female deep poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button3&quot; onclick=&quot;f3()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_3&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
def pov(female, monthly_ubi):
    # Calculate poverty rates for a gender subset given a monthly UBI amount.
    cost = monthly_ubi * total_population * 12
    tax_rate = cost / total_agi_pos  # Divide by positive AGI.
    spm[&quot;new_resources&quot;] = (
        spm.spm_resources - tax_rate * spm.agi_pos + (12 * monthly_ubi * spm.spm_numper)
    )
    person = df[(df.female == female) &amp;amp; (df.a_age &amp;gt; 17)].merge(
        spm[[&quot;spm_id&quot;, &quot;new_resources&quot;]], on=&quot;spm_id&quot;
    )
    return pd.Series(
        dict(
            pov=mdf.poverty_rate(
                person, income=&quot;new_resources&quot;, threshold=&quot;spm_povthreshold&quot;, w=&quot;weight&quot;
            ),
            deep_pov=mdf.deep_poverty_rate(
                person, income=&quot;new_resources&quot;, threshold=&quot;spm_povthreshold&quot;, w=&quot;weight&quot;
            ),
        )
    )


def pov_row(row):
    return pov(row.female, row.monthly_ubi)


gender_ubi = mdf.cartesian_product(
    {&quot;female&quot;: [True, False], &quot;monthly_ubi&quot;: np.arange(0, 1001, 100)}
)
gender_ubi = pd.concat([gender_ubi, gender_ubi.apply(pov_row, axis=1)], axis=1)

gender_ubi_long = gender_ubi.melt(
    id_vars=[&quot;female&quot;, &quot;monthly_ubi&quot;], value_vars=[&quot;pov&quot;, &quot;deep_pov&quot;]
)
gender_ubi_long[&quot;label&quot;] = (
    pd.Series(np.where(gender_ubi_long.female, &quot;Female&quot;, &quot;Male&quot;))
    + &quot; &quot;
    + pd.Series(np.where(gender_ubi_long.variable == &quot;pov&quot;, &quot;poverty&quot;, &quot;deep poverty&quot;))
)
gender_ubi_long.value = gender_ubi_long.value.round(3)

fig = px.line(
    gender_ubi_long,
    x=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;,
    y=&quot;value&quot;,
    color=&quot;label&quot;,
    color_discrete_map=COLOR_MAP,
)

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;Poverty by gender and UBI amount&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income amount (funded by flat income tax)&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;SPM poverty rate (2019)&quot;,
    legend_title=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickformat=&quot;%&quot;,
)

fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;, hovertemplate=None)
fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f3() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_3&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button3&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset3&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/womens-day-2021/2020-03-08-womens-day-2021-asset-3.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset3&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UBI significantly narrows the ratio of poverty and deep poverty rates for adult women compared to adult men.
With a monthly UBI of $500, the rate of women compared to men in poverty is more than halved and the rate of women compared to men in deep poverty is nearly equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button4&quot; onclick=&quot;f4()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_4&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
gender_ratio = gender_ubi.pivot_table(
    values=&quot;pov&quot;, index=[&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;], columns=&quot;female&quot;
).reset_index()
gender_ratio.rename({True: &quot;female&quot;, False: &quot;male&quot;}, axis=1, inplace=True)
gender_ratio[&quot;ratio&quot;] = gender_ratio.female / gender_ratio.male
gender_ratio[&quot;poverty_type&quot;] = &quot;Poverty&quot;
deep_gender_ratio = gender_ubi.pivot_table(
    values=&quot;deep_pov&quot;, index=[&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;], columns=&quot;female&quot;
).reset_index()
deep_gender_ratio.rename({True: &quot;female&quot;, False: &quot;male&quot;}, axis=1, inplace=True)
deep_gender_ratio[&quot;ratio&quot;] = deep_gender_ratio.female / deep_gender_ratio.male
deep_gender_ratio[&quot;poverty_type&quot;] = &quot;Deep poverty&quot;

gender_ratios = pd.concat([gender_ratio, deep_gender_ratio])
gender_ratios.ratio = gender_ratios.ratio.round(2)

fig = px.line(
    gender_ratios,
    x=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;,
    y=&quot;ratio&quot;,
    color=&quot;poverty_type&quot;,
    color_discrete_map=COLOR_MAP,
)

fig.update_yaxes(range=[0.94, 1.18])
fig.add_shape(
    type=&quot;line&quot;,
    x0=0,
    y0=1,
    x1=1000,
    y1=1,
    line=dict(color=LIGHT_GREY, dash=&quot;dash&quot;),
    xref=&quot;x&quot;,
    yref=&quot;y&quot;,
)

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;Poverty disparities by gender with respect to UBI&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income (funded by flat income tax)&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Ratio of women to men SPM poverty rate (2019)&quot;,
    legend_title=&quot;&quot;,
)

fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;, hovertemplate=None)
fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f4() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_4&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button4&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset4&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/womens-day-2021/2020-03-08-womens-day-2021-asset-4.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset4&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gender income gap is inseparable from the issue of care work.
On one hand, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2018/2/19/17018380/gender-wage-gap-childcare-penalty&quot;&gt;“baby penalty”&lt;/a&gt; explains much of the gap, with mothers earning less than fathers while women and men without children have similar earnings.
Meanwhile, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aspe.hhs.gov/system/files/aspe-files/260661/brief2-overviewmtranalyses.pdf&quot;&gt;high marginal tax rates&lt;/a&gt; for low-income parents (due to the phasing out of benefits) discourages work disproportionately of mothers.
A &lt;a href=&quot;https://americancompass.org/essays/home-building-survey-part-2/&quot;&gt;recent poll&lt;/a&gt; found that Americans prefer cash assistance to other family assistance policies like paid family leave, subsidized childcare, wage subsidies, and baby bonds.
Mothers, fathers, and low-income people especially preferred cash assistance, which would likely be more distributionally progressive than other policy options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her &lt;a href=&quot;https://almazzelleke.files.wordpress.com/2014/01/zelleke-institutionalizing-the-universal-caretaker-dec-2008.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; advocating for UBI as compared to other alternatives, political scientist Almaz Zelleke states that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly for advocates of gender equality, a basic income by virtue of its universality goes to both providers and recipients of care, and thus has the best chance of eliminating poverty for the most vulnerable group in contemporary capitalist economies: single mothers and their children. To any feminist, this should be a strong argument in favor of basic income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women provide most of the care work that today goes unpaid and unrecognized.
UBI compensates for that care work, reducing gender inequities and investing in the well-being of the cared-for.
Our analysis suggests that a UBI could be a relevant policy in the greater movement for the social, economic, and political equality of women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:modeling&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Data was gathered from the US Census Bureau’s March Supplement, which covers economic circumstances in 2019. We use the Supplemental Poverty Measure, which incorporates taxes and transfers (including in-kind benefits like SNAP) and adjusts for local housing costs. The flat income tax is applied on positive adjusted gross income. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:modeling&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;katarina&quot;, &quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="gender" />
      
        <category term="poverty" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Women are 17% more likely to be in poverty than women, but basic income would shrink the gap.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The effect of universal basic income on a novel measure of the racial wealth gap</title>
      <link href="/racial-wealth-gap-ks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The effect of universal basic income on a novel measure of the racial wealth gap" />
      <published>2021-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/racial-wealth-gap-ks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/racial-wealth-gap-ks">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large racial wealth gap traces its roots to slavery, redlining, and other discriminatory policies, and persists largely due to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-03-21/how-income-inequality-feeds-the-racial-wealth-gap&quot;&gt;racial income gaps&lt;/a&gt;.
In honor of Black History month, we explore how closing part of this income gap with a universal basic income would affect the racial wealth gap, using novel measurements that consider how Black and White families differ across the full wealth distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two most common measures of the racial wealth gap simply compare mean and median wealth between White and Black families.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:head&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:head&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Based on the 2019 Survey of Consumer Finances&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:scf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:scf&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, White families have mean wealth 5.7 times that of Black families, and median wealth 6.4 times that of Black families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import warnings

import numpy as np
import pandas as pd
import plotly.express as px
import plotly.graph_objects as go
import plotly.io as pio
import ubicenter
from plotly.subplots import make_subplots

cdfs = pd.read_csv(&quot;data/cdfs.csv&quot;)
ubi_summary = pd.read_csv(&quot;data/ubi_summary.csv&quot;)
nw_quant = pd.read_csv(&quot;data/deciles.csv&quot;)


# Define UBI Center colors
BLUE = &quot;#1976D2&quot;
DARK_BLUE = &quot;#1565C0&quot;
LIGHT_BLUE = &quot;#90CAF9&quot;
GRAY = &quot;#BDBDBD&quot;
DARK_GRAY = &quot;#616161&quot;
BARELY_BLUE = &quot;#E3F2FD&quot;

colors = [BLUE, DARK_BLUE, LIGHT_BLUE, GRAY, BARELY_BLUE]

bl = ubi_summary.iloc[0].round(-2)
params = pd.DataFrame(
    {
        &quot;Mean&quot;: {
            &quot;White&quot;: bl.white_mean_networth_pa,
            &quot;Black&quot;: bl.black_mean_networth_pa,
        },
        &quot;Median&quot;: {
            &quot;White&quot;: bl.white_median_networth_pa,
            &quot;Black&quot;: bl.black_median_networth_pa,
        },
    }
)

fig = go.Figure(
    data=[
        go.Bar(name=&quot;White&quot;, x=params.T.index, y=params.T[&quot;White&quot;], marker_color=GRAY),
        go.Bar(name=&quot;Black&quot;, x=params.T.index, y=params.T[&quot;Black&quot;], marker_color=BLUE),
    ]
)

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;Traditional measures of the racial wealth gap&quot;,
    hovermode=&quot;x&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    legend=dict(yanchor=&quot;top&quot;, y=0.99, xanchor=&quot;left&quot;, x=0.75),
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Matt Bruenig pointed out in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peoplespolicyproject.org/2020/06/29/the-racial-wealth-gap-is-about-the-upper-classes/&quot;&gt;June 2020 piece&lt;/a&gt;, the mean wealth gap is largely shaped by overall wealth inequality, with over 70 percent of both Black and White families’ wealth held by the top decile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
hovertemplate = &quot;%{x:.1f}%&quot;

fig = px.bar(
    nw_quant[nw_quant.variable.isin([&quot;White&quot;, &quot;Black&quot;])],
    y=&quot;percentile&quot;,
    x=&quot;value&quot;,
    color=&quot;variable&quot;,
    labels={
        &quot;percentile&quot;: &quot;Percent receiving benefit&quot;,
        &quot;value&quot;: &quot;Share of within-group wealth&quot;,
    },
    orientation=&quot;h&quot;,
    barmode=&quot;group&quot;,
    color_discrete_map={&quot;White&quot;: GRAY, &quot;Black&quot;: BLUE},
)

fig.update_traces(hovertemplate=&quot;Share of Wealth: &quot; + hovertemplate)

# apply formatting
fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;Within-race wealth inequality&quot;,
    hovermode=&quot;y&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Share of total within-group wealth held by decile&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Decile of wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
    xaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    legend_title=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_dtick=1,
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the median tells us where the middle of the distributions lay, it can obscure what is going on throughout the rest of the distribution.
To visualize a variable’s distribution in full, we can turn to the cumulative distribution function (CDF), which shows the population share with less than a specified value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following graph shows how to interpret a CDF graph of of wealth per adult for all families in the U.S. (Note that while we have logarithmically transformed the x-axis, the y-axis remains linear.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button3&quot; onclick=&quot;f3()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_3&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
all_hh = cdfs.loc[cdfs.ubi_mo == 0].copy(deep=True)

# select 5000k
med = all_hh.loc[all_hh[&quot;networth_pa_new&quot;] == 50000, :].copy(deep=True)
med[&quot;x&quot;] = np.log10(med.networth_pa_new)
med[&quot;y&quot;] = med.loc[:, &quot;total_share&quot;]

# plot curve
fig = px.line(x=all_hh.networth_pa_new, y=all_hh.total_share.round(3))
# change line coloar
fig[&quot;data&quot;][0][&quot;line&quot;][&quot;color&quot;] = BLUE

# add explanation for arrow pointing to y-axis
fig.add_annotation(
    x=2,
    y=med.y.values[0],
    text=&quot;Look at y-axis to see share of families &lt;br /&gt; whose wealth is below the x-value&quot;,
    showarrow=True,
    arrowhead=0,
    ay=-50,
    ax=150,
    font=dict(size=16),
)

# add dotted line pointing from x-axis to point
fig.add_annotation(
    x=med.x.values[0],
    y=0,
    text=&quot;For a given wealth on the x-axis&quot;,
    showarrow=True,
    arrowhead=0,
    # yshift=-60,
    # xshift=-130,
    ax=160,
    ay=-50,
    font=dict(size=16),
)

# add red arrow pointing from x-axis to point
fig.add_annotation(
    x=med.x.values[0],  # arrows' head
    y=med.y.values[0],  # arrows' head
    ax=med.x.values[0],  # arrows' tail
    ay=0,  # arrows' tail
    xref=&quot;x&quot;,
    yref=&quot;y&quot;,
    axref=&quot;x&quot;,
    ayref=&quot;y&quot;,
    text=&quot;&quot;,  # if you want only the arrow
    showarrow=True,
    arrowhead=2,
    arrowsize=2,
    arrowwidth=1,
    arrowcolor=GRAY,
)

# add arrow pointing from point to y-axis
fig.add_annotation(
    x=2,  # arrows' head
    y=med.y.values[0],  # arrows' head
    ax=med.x.values[0],  # arrows' tail
    ay=med.y.values[0],  # arrows' tail
    xref=&quot;x&quot;,
    yref=&quot;y&quot;,
    axref=&quot;x&quot;,
    ayref=&quot;y&quot;,
    text=&quot;&quot;,  # if you want only the arrow
    showarrow=True,
    arrowhead=2,
    arrowsize=2,
    arrowwidth=1,
    arrowcolor=GRAY,
)

fig.update_layout(
    showlegend=False,
    title=&quot;Cumulative wealth distribution&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Share of families with less than value in wealth&quot;,
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    hovermode=&quot;x&quot;,
)

fig.update_xaxes(
    dict(
        range=[2, 9],
        autorange=False,
        showspikes=False,  # Show spike line for x-axis
        # Format spike
        spikethickness=1,
        spikedash=&quot;dot&quot;,
        spikecolor=&quot;grey&quot;,
        spikemode=&quot;toaxis&quot;,
    ),
    type=&quot;log&quot;,
)
fig.update_yaxes(
    dict(
        range=[0, 1.01],
        showspikes=True,
        spikethickness=1,
        spikedash=&quot;dot&quot;,
        spikecolor=&quot;grey&quot;,
        spikemode=&quot;toaxis&quot;,
    )
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f3() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_3&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button3&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset3&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-3.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset3&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how can we compare the distributions of wealth between Black and White families?
The two-sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) statistical test offers a way to test the difference between two distributions.
The KS statistic, or D-statistic (for “distance”), is the maximum absolute vertical distance between two CDFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One advantage to this statistical method is that it is quite simple to explain visually.
The below chart plots the CDF for White and Black families.
The dotted line drawn between the two curves shows where the vertical distance between them is at its greatest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button4&quot; onclick=&quot;f4()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_4&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
with warnings.catch_warnings():  # ignore &quot;FutureWarning&quot;
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Ignore numpy 'FutureWarning' :
    &quot;Using a non-tuple sequence for multidimensional indexing is deprecated;
    use `arr[tuple(seq)]` instead of `arr[seq]`. In the future this will be
    interpreted as an array index, `arr[np.array(seq)]`, which will result
    either in an error or a different result.&quot;
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    warnings.filterwarnings(&quot;ignore&quot;, category=FutureWarning)

    # Create traces
    fig = go.Figure()

    # create df for baseline
    cdfs_bl = cdfs[cdfs.ubi_mo == 0]
    # plot ECDFs
    fig.add_trace(
        go.Scatter(
            x=cdfs_bl.networth_pa_new,
            y=cdfs_bl.white_share.round(3),
            name=&quot;White&quot;,
            marker_color=GRAY,
        )
    )
    fig.add_trace(
        go.Scatter(
            x=cdfs_bl.networth_pa_new,
            y=cdfs_bl.black_share.round(3),
            name=&quot;Black&quot;,
            marker_color=BLUE,
        )
    )

    # define ks_stat
    ks_stat = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == 0, &quot;d_stat_cand&quot;].max()

    # find networth where the d-statistic is found
    max_x = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == 0, &quot;networth_pa_new&quot;].max()

    # find networth where abs distance between ecdfs is is @  max
    y1 = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == 0, &quot;white_share&quot;].max()
    y0 = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == 0, &quot;black_share&quot;].max()

    # # add a dashed line showing where max abs distance between ECDFs is

    dash_names = &quot;Max abs. distance between CDFs&quot;
    dash_color = &quot;black&quot;
    fig.add_trace(
        go.Scatter(
            x=[max_x, max_x],
            y=[y0, y1],
            mode=&quot;lines+text&quot;,
            line={&quot;dash&quot;: &quot;dot&quot;, &quot;color&quot;: dash_color, &quot;width&quot;: 2},
            visible=True,
            name=dash_names,
            text=[&quot;D-statistic: &quot; + str(round(ks_stat, 3)) + &quot;        &quot;, None],
            textfont=dict(size=16),
            textposition=&quot;top left&quot;,
            showlegend=False,
        )
    )

    fig.add_annotation(
        x=np.log10(max_x),
        y=(y1 + y0) / 2,
        text=&quot;The Kolmogorov-Smirnov D-statistic &lt;br /&gt;&quot;
        + &quot;is the maximum absolute vertical &lt;br /&gt;&quot;
        + &quot;distance between the two curves&quot;,
        showarrow=True,
        arrowhead=3,
        yshift=1,
        ax=200,
        bordercolor=&quot;#c7c7c7&quot;,
        borderwidth=2,
        borderpad=4,
        bgcolor=&quot;dark blue&quot;,
        opacity=1,
        font=dict(size=16),
    )

    fig.update_layout(
        title=&quot;Cumulative distribution function (CDF) of wealth by race&quot;,
        xaxis_title=&quot;Wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
        yaxis_title=&quot;Share of families with less than value in wealth&quot;,
        yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
        yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
        xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
        legend={&quot;traceorder&quot;: &quot;reversed&quot;},
    )

    fig.update_xaxes(type=&quot;log&quot;)
    fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
    fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f4() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_4&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button4&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset4&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-4.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset4&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows us that approximately 65.9% of Black families have a wealth of less than $50,000 per adult, whereas only 33.3% of White families fall below that line.
As we will see, the threshold can be at any point along these curves; the KS statistic is the value measuring the size of the gap where the gap is the largest, at 0.326 (the actual wealth value corresponding to the D-statistic was $50,888).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following model, we simulate how saving a total of one year’s UBI payments could change the racial wealth gap. We apply a flat tax on all income to fund the UBI program, and subtract each family’s new tax payment from their wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the bottom graph, you can see the vertical distance between the two curves at each point along the x-axis from $0 to $2,000 per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button5&quot; onclick=&quot;f5()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_5&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
def ecdf_slider(data):
    # Create traces
    fig = go.Figure()

    # create empty list for payment size for sliders
    payments = []
    ks_stats = []
    max_xs = []

    # create 2 subplots
    fig = make_subplots(
        rows=2,
        cols=1,
        shared_xaxes=False,
        # Apply x axis title elsewhere so it doesn't interfere with slider.
        y_title=&quot;Share of families with less than value in wealth&quot;,
    )

    for i, step in enumerate(data.ubi_mo.unique()):
        # append payment to list
        payments.append(step)
        step_data = data[data.ubi_mo == step]
        # add trace 0
        fig.add_trace(
            go.Scatter(
                x=step_data.networth_pa_new,
                y=step_data.white_share.round(3),
                name=&quot;White&quot;,
                visible=False,
                marker_color=GRAY,
            ),
            row=1,
            col=1,
        )
        # add trace 1
        fig.add_trace(
            go.Scatter(
                x=step_data.networth_pa_new,
                y=step_data.black_share.round(3),
                name=&quot;Black&quot;,
                visible=False,
                marker_color=BLUE,
            ),
            row=1,
            col=1,
        )
        # append ks-statistics to list
        ks_stat = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == step, &quot;d_stat_cand&quot;].values[0]
        ks_stats.append(ks_stat)

        # add plot to candidate
        # add trace 2, the d-statistic candidates
        fig.add_trace(
            go.Scatter(
                x=step_data.networth_pa_new,
                y=step_data.d_stat_cand.round(3),
                mode=&quot;lines&quot;,
                visible=False,
                name=&quot;Absolute distance between CDFs&quot;,
                marker_color=LIGHT_BLUE,
            ),
            row=2,
            col=1,
        )

        # find networth where the d-statistic
        max_x = (
            ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == step, &quot;networth_pa_new&quot;]
            .iloc[0]
            .round(3)
        )
        max_xs.append(max_x)

        # find networth where abs distance between ecdfs is is @  max
        y1 = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == step, &quot;white_share&quot;].iloc[0].round(3)
        y0 = ubi_summary.loc[ubi_summary.ubi_mo == step, &quot;black_share&quot;].iloc[0].round(3)

        dash_names = &quot;Max abs. distance between CDFs&quot;
        dash_color = &quot;black&quot;
        # dotted line between two curves
        fig.add_trace(
            go.Scatter(
                x=[max_x, max_x],
                y=[y0, y1],
                mode=&quot;lines+text&quot;,
                line={&quot;dash&quot;: &quot;dot&quot;, &quot;color&quot;: dash_color, &quot;width&quot;: 2},
                visible=False,
                name=dash_names,
                text=[&quot;D-statistic: &quot; + str(round(ks_stat, 3)) + &quot;     &quot;, None],
                textfont=dict(size=16),
                textposition=&quot;top left&quot;,
                showlegend=False,
            ),
            row=1,
            col=1,
        )
        # dotted line to peak on bottom chart
        fig.add_trace(
            go.Scatter(
                x=[round(max_x, 3), round(max_x, 3)],
                y=[0, round(y0 - y1, 3)],
                mode=&quot;lines&quot;,
                line={&quot;dash&quot;: &quot;dot&quot;, &quot;color&quot;: dash_color, &quot;width&quot;: 2},
                visible=False,
                name=dash_names,
                showlegend=False,
            ),
            row=2,
            col=1,
        )

    # define number of plots in each step
    n = 5
    # Make first n traces visible
    for i in range(0, n):
        fig.data[i].visible = True

    # Create and add slider
    steps = []
    for i in range(0, len(fig.data), n):
        step = dict(
            method=&quot;update&quot;,
            args=[{&quot;visible&quot;: [False] * len(fig.data)},],  # layout attribute
            label=(&quot;$&quot; + str(payments[i // n])),
        )
        for j in range(0, n):
            step[&quot;args&quot;][0][&quot;visible&quot;][i + j] = True  # Toggle i'th trace to &quot;visible&quot;
        steps.append(step)
    sliders = [
        dict(
            active=0,
            currentvalue={&quot;prefix&quot;: &quot;Monthly universal basic income payment: &quot;},
            pad={&quot;t&quot;: 50},
            steps=steps,
        )
    ]

    fig.update_traces(xaxis=&quot;x1&quot;)

    # update shapes
    fig.update_shapes(dict(xref=&quot;x&quot;, yref=&quot;y&quot;))

    # fig.update_yaxes(showspikes=True)
    fig.update_layout(
        sliders=sliders,
        xaxis=dict(
            visible=True,
            type=&quot;log&quot;,
            range=[2, 9],
            autorange=False,
            showspikes=True,  # Show spike line for X-axis
            # Format spike
            spikethickness=2,
            spikedash=&quot;dot&quot;,
            spikecolor=&quot;#999999&quot;,
            spikemode=&quot;across&quot;,
        ),
        title=&quot;The Kolmogorov-Smirnov measure of the racial wealth gap&quot;,
        xaxis_title=&quot;Wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
        hovermode=&quot;x&quot;,
        xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    )

    fig.update_xaxes(
        visible=True,
        type=&quot;log&quot;,
        row=2,
        col=1,
    )
    fig.update_yaxes(
        dict(
            range=[0, 1],
            autorange=False,
            showspikes=False,  # Show spike line for y-axis
            # Format spike
            spikethickness=2,
            spikedash=&quot;dot&quot;,
            spikecolor=&quot;#999999&quot;,
            spikemode=&quot;toaxis&quot;,
        ),
        row=2,
        col=1,
    )

    return ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)


with warnings.catch_warnings():  # ignore &quot;FutureWarning&quot;
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Ignore numpy 'FutureWarning' :
    &quot;Using a non-tuple sequence for multidimensional indexing is deprecated;
    use `arr[tuple(seq)]` instead of `arr[seq]`. In the future this will be
    interpreted as an array index, `arr[np.array(seq)]`, which will result
    either in an error or a different result.&quot;
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    warnings.filterwarnings(&quot;ignore&quot;, category=FutureWarning)
    fig = ecdf_slider(cdfs)
    fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f5() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_5&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button5&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset5&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-5.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset5&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is notable that while the KS D-statistics declines overall, it fluctuates until we get to $500 payments, at which point the D-statistic begins a steady decline to minimum of 0.300 under the $2,000 monthly benefit scenario.
This is because the distances between the two curves are much larger around the center of the distributions than around the tails, thus the changes in the KS test are not picking up changes at lower incomes, where the curves were much closer together to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our simulations, the wealth point at which the curves are furthest apart increases with the UBI amount.
The wealth at which the gap is the biggest rises to just above $121,000, from $50,000 at baseline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button6&quot; onclick=&quot;f6()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_6&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = make_subplots(
    rows=2,
    cols=1,
    shared_xaxes=True,
    x_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income payment&quot;,
    subplot_titles=[
        &quot;Black vs White wealth KS statistic&quot;,
        &quot;Wealth where Black and White cumulative distributions differ most&quot;,
    ],
)

fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary.ubi_mo,
        y=ubi_summary.d_stat_cand.round(3),
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;KS statistic&quot;,
        marker_color=BLUE,
    ),
    row=1,
    col=1,
)
fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary.ubi_mo,
        y=ubi_summary.networth_pa_new,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;Wealth at KS D-stat&quot;,
        marker_color=LIGHT_BLUE,
    ),
    row=2,
    col=1,
)

fig.update_layout(showlegend=False, hovermode=&quot;x&quot;, xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f6() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_6&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button6&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset6&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-6.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset6&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, without UBI the median White family has $6.45 for every $1 held by the median Black family. Under a $1,000 monthly payment, this falls to $3.49 for every $1, and further down to $2.64 with a $2,000 monthly payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The median wealth for White families rises from $115,103 without a UBI to $119,425 under a $1,000 monthly payment, and rises to $127,505 with a $2,000 monthly payment.
For Black families, a $1,000 UBI nearly doubles the median wealth, from $17,853 to $34,183, and a $2,000 monthly benefit grows it further to $48,310.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that the median wealth per adult&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:peradult&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:peradult&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; rises among White families, it merely rises by less than that of Black families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button7&quot; onclick=&quot;f7()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_7&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = go.Figure()

hovertemplate = &quot;$%{y:.0f}&quot;

fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary.ubi_mo,
        y=ubi_summary.black_median_networth_pa,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;Black&quot;,
        marker_color=BLUE,
        hovertemplate=hovertemplate,
    )
)
fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary.ubi_mo,
        y=ubi_summary.white_median_networth_pa,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;White&quot;,
        marker_color=GRAY,
        hovertemplate=hovertemplate,
    )
)

ymax = ubi_summary[[&quot;black_median_networth_pa&quot;, &quot;white_median_networth_pa&quot;]].max().max() * 1.1

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;How UBI affects median wealth by race&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income payment&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Median wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    yaxis_range=[0, ymax],
    legend={&quot;traceorder&quot;: &quot;reversed&quot;},
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f7() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_7&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button7&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset7&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-7.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset7&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the rising median wealth for White families under the same UBI, mean wealth for White families declines from $557,216 without any UBI to 555,135 under a $1,000 monthly payment, and falls further to $553,054 with a $2,000 monthly payment.
For Black families, the mean wealth rises from $97,167 to $104,768 with a $1,000 benefit, and further to $112,369 with a $2,000 benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button8&quot; onclick=&quot;f8()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_8&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = go.Figure()

hovertemplate = &quot;$%{y:.0f}&quot;

fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary.ubi_mo,
        y=ubi_summary.black_mean_networth_pa,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;Black&quot;,
        marker_color=BLUE,
        hovertemplate=hovertemplate,
    )
)
fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary.ubi_mo,
        y=ubi_summary.white_mean_networth_pa,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;White&quot;,
        marker_color=GRAY,
        hovertemplate=hovertemplate,
    )
)

ymax = (
    ubi_summary[[&quot;black_mean_networth_pa&quot;, &quot;white_mean_networth_pa&quot;]].max().max() * 1.1
)

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;How UBI affects mean wealth by race&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income payment&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Mean wealth per adult (2019)&quot;,
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    yaxis_range=[0, ymax],
    legend={&quot;traceorder&quot;: &quot;reversed&quot;},
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f8() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_8&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button8&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset8&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-8.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset8&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we look at the share of families that fall below $50,000 per adult, the point at which those two curves were further apart in our baseline scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button9&quot; onclick=&quot;f9()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_9&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = go.Figure()
hovertemplate = &quot;%{y:.0f}%&quot;

fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary[&quot;ubi_mo&quot;],
        y=ubi_summary[&quot;black_share_above_50k&quot;] * 100,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;Black&quot;,
        marker_color=BLUE,
        hovertemplate=hovertemplate,
    )
)
fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=ubi_summary[&quot;ubi_mo&quot;],
        y=ubi_summary[&quot;white_share_above_50k&quot;] * 100,
        mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
        name=&quot;White&quot;,
        marker_color=GRAY,
        hovertemplate=hovertemplate,
    )
)

ymax = (
    ubi_summary[[&quot;white_share_above_50k&quot;, &quot;black_share_above_50k&quot;]].max().max()
    * 100
    * 1.1
)

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;How UBI affects the share of families with wealth above $50,000 by race&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income payment&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Share of families with wealth above $50,000 per adult (2019)&quot;,
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    yaxis_range=[0, ymax],
    legend={&quot;traceorder&quot;: &quot;reversed&quot;},
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f9() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_9&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button9&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset9&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-9.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset9&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The share of Black families with a per adult networth of over $50,000 rises from 65.9 percent to 61.2 percent when we raise the monthly UBI to $1,000 monthly, and falls further to 51.7 percent when we raise the benefit to $2,000 monthly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the scenarios we explore, the outcomes for Black families improve in the share of families with wealth per adult below $50,000 declines, median family wealth increases.
In the final plot below, you can explore the relative changes in all of the metrics we’ve chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button10&quot; onclick=&quot;f10()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_10&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = go.Figure()


def trace(col, chg_col, name, string, color):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Args:
        col: Column name.
        chg_col: Column name of change.
        name: Name of column for printing.
        string: Formatting of customdata[1].
        color: Line color.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    fig.add_trace(
        go.Scatter(
            x=ubi_summary[&quot;ubi_mo&quot;],
            y=ubi_summary[chg_col] * 100,
            mode=&quot;lines+markers&quot;,
            name=name,
            marker_color=color,
            marker=dict(size=5),
            customdata=np.stack((ubi_summary.ubi_mo, ubi_summary[col]), axis=-1),
            hovertemplate=name
            + &quot;: &quot;
            + string
            + &quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
            + &quot;Percent change: %{y:.0f}%&lt;br /&gt;&quot;,
        )
    )


trace(
    &quot;white_mean_nw_as_pct_of_mean_black&quot;,
    &quot;white_mean_nw_as_pct_of_mean_black_pc&quot;,
    &quot;White/Black mean wealth&quot;,
    &quot;%{customdata[1]: .1f}&quot;,
    DARK_GRAY,
)
# median wealth
trace(
    &quot;white_median_nw_as_pct_of_median_black&quot;,
    &quot;white_median_nw_as_pct_of_median_black_pc&quot;,
    &quot;White/Black median wealth&quot;,
    &quot;%{customdata[1]: .1f}&quot;,
    GRAY,
)
trace(
    &quot;d_stat_cand&quot;, &quot;d_stat_cand_pc&quot;, &quot;KS statistic&quot;, &quot;%{customdata[1]: .3f}&quot;, DARK_BLUE
)
trace(
    &quot;white_share_above_50k_pct_of_black&quot;,
    &quot;white_share_above_50k_pct_of_black_pc&quot;,
    &quot;White/Black share of families over $50k&quot;,
    &quot;%{customdata[1]: .1f}&quot;,
    LIGHT_BLUE,
)

fig.update_layout(
    title=&quot;How UBI affects different measures of the racial wealth gap&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income payment&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Percent change in measure over baseline (2019)&quot;,
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
    xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
)

fig = ubicenter.format_fig(fig, show = False)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f10() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_10&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button10&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset10&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-wealth-gap-ks/2021-02-28-racial-wealth-gap-ks-asset-10.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset10&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these metrics aren’t truly comparable, we can see that the KS statistic is more stubborn than other measures, especially the gap in median wealth.
Median Black wealth is so low that even modest redistribution can close that gap quickly, but larger gaps in the middle of the distribution will persist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will continue this line of research, especially longer-term dynamic analysis to reflect the accumulative nature of wealth.
Our simplifying assumption that the entire tax and transfer system flows straight to wealth, rather than consumption, may exaggerate these trends given propensities to consume decrease with wealth. But recurring redistribution would likely have a significantly larger effect in closing the gap, even accounting for consumption.
UBI isn’t the only policy that can reduce racial wealth disparities, but it certainly helps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:head&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;White and Black families are families headed by a White and Black person, respectively. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:head&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:scf&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We used the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.org&quot;&gt;Policy Simulation Library&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/scf&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/microdf&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;microdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Python packages for extracting and processing this data in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/UBICenter/blog/blob/master/jb/20210228/data/gen_data.py&quot;&gt;this script&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:scf&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:peradult&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Family wealth conventionally adjusts for number of adults to avoid distorting statistics due to marriage patterns; for example, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.credit-suisse.com/about-us/en/reports-research/global-wealth-report.html&quot;&gt;Credit Suisse’s Global Net Worth Report&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:peradult&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;will&quot;, &quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="race" />
      
        <category term="wealth" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Going beyond mean and median.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Basic income would shrink racial poverty disparities</title>
      <link href="/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic income would shrink racial poverty disparities" />
      <published>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. is remembered chiefly for his leadership of the civil rights movement,
but toward the end of his life, King extended this leadership to the cause of poverty.
In his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thekinglegacy.org/books/where-do-we-go-here-chaos-or-community&quot;&gt;final book&lt;/a&gt;,
he wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-{epigraph}&quot;&gt;The time has come for us to civilize ourselves by the total, direct and immediate abolition of poverty [...] 
I'm now convinced that the simplest approach will prove to be the most effective — the solution to poverty is to abolish it directly by a now widely discussed measure: the guaranteed income.

-- Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., *Where Do We Go From Here: Chaos or Community?* (1967)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We honor King’s call by showing how a universal basic income (UBI), funded by a flat income tax, would not only reduce overall poverty, but also shrink the poverty disparities between Black and White people. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:modeling&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:modeling&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black Americans today are 75 percent more likely to be in poverty than White Americans, with a rate of 18.4 percent compared to 10.5 percent.
A $250 monthly UBI would cut both Black and White poverty roughly in half (this is similar to what we found in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/how-universal-basic-income-would-affect-the-black-white-poverty-and-wealth-gaps-452e2af1497b&quot;&gt;July 2020 post&lt;/a&gt;, which used older data and did not simulate taxes to fund the UBI).
A $1,000 monthly UBI funded by a flat income tax would reduce poverty for both White and Black people to about 1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import pandas as pd
import numpy as np
import microdf as mdf
import plotly.express as px

SPM_COLS = [
    &quot;spm_&quot; + i for i in [&quot;id&quot;, &quot;weight&quot;, &quot;povthreshold&quot;, &quot;resources&quot;, &quot;numper&quot;]
]
raw = pd.read_csv(
    &quot;https://github.com/MaxGhenis/datarepo/raw/master/pppub20.csv.gz&quot;,
    usecols=[&quot;PRDTRACE&quot;, &quot;MARSUPWT&quot;, &quot;AGI&quot;] + [i.upper() for i in SPM_COLS],
)
person = raw.copy(deep=True)
person.columns = person.columns.str.lower()
person[&quot;weight&quot;] = person.marsupwt / 100
person.spm_weight /= 100
person = person.rename(columns={&quot;prdtrace&quot;: &quot;race&quot;})
# Add indicators for white only and black only (not considering other races).
person[&quot;white&quot;] = person.race == 1
person[&quot;black&quot;] = person.race == 2
# Limit to positive AGI.
person[&quot;agi_pos&quot;] = np.maximum(person.agi, 0)
# Need total population to calculate UBI and total AGI for required tax rate.
total_population = person.weight.sum()
total_agi = mdf.weighted_sum(person, &quot;agi_pos&quot;, &quot;weight&quot;)
# Sum up AGI for each SPM unit and merge that back to person level.
spm = person.groupby(SPM_COLS)[[&quot;agi_pos&quot;, &quot;white&quot;, &quot;black&quot;]].sum()
spm.columns = [&quot;spm_&quot; + i for i in spm.columns]
# Merge these back to person to calculate population in White and Black spmus.
person = person.merge(spm, on=&quot;spm_id&quot;)
pop_in_race_spmu = pd.Series(
    {
        &quot;Black&quot;: person[person.spm_black &amp;gt; 0].weight.sum(),
        &quot;White&quot;: person[person.spm_white &amp;gt; 0].weight.sum(),
    }
)
spm.reset_index(inplace=True)


def pov_gap(df, resources, threshold, weight):
    # df: Should be SPM-unit level.
    gaps = np.maximum(df[threshold] - df[resources], 0)
    return (gaps * df[weight]).sum()


def pov(race, monthly_ubi):
    # Total cost and associated tax rate.
    cost = monthly_ubi * total_population * 12
    tax_rate = cost / total_agi
    # Calculate new tax, UBI and resources per SPM unit.
    spm[&quot;new_spm_resources&quot;] = (
        spm.spm_resources - 
        (tax_rate * spm.spm_agi_pos) +  # New tax
        (12 * monthly_ubi * spm.spm_numper))  # UBI
    # Merge back to person.
    person2 = person.merge(spm[[&quot;spm_id&quot;, &quot;new_spm_resources&quot;]], on=&quot;spm_id&quot;)
    # Based on new resources, calculate
    person2[&quot;new_poor&quot;] = person2.new_spm_resources &amp;lt; person2.spm_povthreshold
    # Calculate poverty rate for specified race.
    poverty_rate = mdf.weighted_mean(
        person2[person2[race.lower()]], &quot;new_poor&quot;, &quot;weight&quot;
    )
    # Calculate poverty gap for specified race.
    poverty_gap = pov_gap(
        spm[spm[&quot;spm_&quot; + race.lower()] &amp;gt; 0], &quot;new_spm_resources&quot;,
        &quot;spm_povthreshold&quot;, &quot;spm_weight&quot;
    )
    poverty_gap_per_capita = (poverty_gap / pop_in_race_spmu[race])

    return pd.Series({
        &quot;poverty_rate&quot;: poverty_rate,
        &quot;poverty_gap_per_capita&quot;: poverty_gap_per_capita
    })


def pov_row(row):
    return pov(row.race, row.monthly_ubi)


summary = mdf.cartesian_product(
    {&quot;race&quot;: [&quot;White&quot;, &quot;Black&quot;], &quot;monthly_ubi&quot;: np.arange(0, 1001, 50)}
)
summary = pd.concat([summary, summary.apply(pov_row, axis=1)], axis=1)
# Format results.
summary.poverty_rate = 100 * summary.poverty_rate.round(3)
summary.poverty_gap_per_capita = summary.poverty_gap_per_capita.round(0)
wide = summary.pivot_table(
    [&quot;poverty_rate&quot;, &quot;poverty_gap_per_capita&quot;], &quot;monthly_ubi&quot;, &quot;race&quot;
)
wide.columns = [&quot;pg_black&quot;, &quot;pg_white&quot;, &quot;pr_black&quot;, &quot;pr_white&quot;]
wide[&quot;pg_ratio&quot;] = (wide.pg_black / wide.pg_white).round(2)
wide[&quot;pr_ratio&quot;] = (wide.pr_black / wide.pr_white).round(2)
wide.reset_index(inplace=True)
ratios = wide.melt(id_vars=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;, value_vars=[&quot;pr_ratio&quot;, &quot;pg_ratio&quot;])
# Change for chart.
ratios.variable.replace({&quot;pr_ratio&quot;: &quot;Poverty rate&quot;,
                         &quot;pg_ratio&quot;: &quot;Poverty gap per capita&quot;},
                        inplace=True)


def add_ubi_center_logo(fig, x=0.98, y=-0.14):
    fig.add_layout_image(
        dict(
            source=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/UBICenter/blog/master/jb/_static/ubi_center_logo_wide_blue.png&quot;,
            # See https://github.com/plotly/plotly.py/issues/2975.
            # source=&quot;../_static/ubi_center_logo_wide_blue.png&quot;,
            xref=&quot;paper&quot;, yref=&quot;paper&quot;,
            x=x, y=y,
            sizex=0.12, sizey=0.12,
            xanchor=&quot;right&quot;, yanchor=&quot;bottom&quot;
        )
    )


def line_graph(
    df,
    x,
    y,
    color,
    title,
    xaxis_title,
    yaxis_title,
    color_discrete_map,
    yaxis_ticksuffix,
    yaxis_tickprefix,
):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Style for line graphs.
    
    Arguments
    df: DataFrame with data to be plotted.
    x: The string representing the column in df that holds the new spending in billions.
    y: The string representing the column in df that holds the poverty rate.
    color: The string representing the UBI type.
    xaxis_title: The string represnting the xaxis-title.
    yaxis_title: The string representing the yaxis-title.
    
    Returns
    Nothing. Shows the plot.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    fig = px.line(
        df, x=x, y=y, color=color, color_discrete_map=color_discrete_map
    )
    fig.update_layout(
        title=title,
        xaxis_title=xaxis_title,
        yaxis_title=yaxis_title,
        yaxis_ticksuffix=yaxis_ticksuffix,
        yaxis_tickprefix=yaxis_tickprefix,
        font=dict(family=&quot;Roboto&quot;),
        hovermode=&quot;x&quot;,
        xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
        plot_bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;,
        legend_title_text=&quot;&quot;,
        height=600,
        width=1000,
    )

    fig.update_layout(
        legend=dict(yanchor=&quot;top&quot;, y=0.99, xanchor=&quot;left&quot;, x=0.9)
    )

    fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;, hovertemplate=None)
    
    add_ubi_center_logo(fig)

    return fig
    

DARK_BLUE = &quot;#1565C0&quot;
GRAY = &quot;#9E9E9E&quot;
DARK_GREEN = &quot;#388E3C&quot;
LIGHT_GREEN = &quot;#66BB6A&quot;
CONFIG = {&quot;displayModeBar&quot;: False}

fig = line_graph(
    df=summary,
    x=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;,
    y=&quot;poverty_rate&quot;,
    color=&quot;race&quot;,
    title=&quot;Black and White poverty rate by UBI amount&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income funded by flat income tax&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;SPM poverty rate (2019)&quot;,
    color_discrete_map={&quot;White&quot;: GRAY, &quot;Black&quot;: DARK_BLUE},
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
)
fig.show(config=CONFIG)
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021/2021-01-18-racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poverty rate only tells part of the story, though.
When someone goes from deep in poverty to just below the poverty line, the poverty rate is left unchanged, despite the person’s material conditions improving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative measure is the &lt;em&gt;poverty gap&lt;/em&gt;, which aggregates each household’s difference between its resources and its poverty threshold. This counts improvements of people who remain in poverty, and can be thought of as the total amount of money required to lift everyone out of poverty, if that money could be perfectly targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying this measure and adjusting for population differences, the Black poverty gap exceeds the White poverty gap by 50 percent: $654 per person, vs. $434 per person.
Given a $250 monthly UBI, which cuts poverty rates in half, poverty gaps also fall by about half, and the difference falls such that the Black poverty gap is about 36 percent higher.
For UBIs above $600 per month, the Black poverty gap even falls below the White poverty gap, likely due to Black people living in areas with lower-cost housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = line_graph(
    df=summary,
    x=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;,
    y=&quot;poverty_gap_per_capita&quot;,
    color=&quot;race&quot;,
    title=&quot;Black and White poverty gap per capita by UBI amount&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income funded by flat income tax&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Poverty gap per capita (2019)&quot;,
    color_discrete_map={&quot;White&quot;: GRAY, &quot;Black&quot;: DARK_BLUE},
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
)
fig.show(config=CONFIG)
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021/2021-01-18-racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing these together, it’s clear that UBIs don’t only reduce poverty rates and poverty gaps for both races, but also bring them closer together, reducing racial disparities in poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button3&quot; onclick=&quot;f3()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_3&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = line_graph(
    df=ratios,
    x=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;,
    y=&quot;value&quot;,
    color=&quot;variable&quot;,
    title=&quot;Black poverty relative to White poverty by UBI amount&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly universal basic income funded by flat income tax&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;Ratio of Black to White poverty measure (2019)&quot;,
    color_discrete_map={&quot;Poverty rate&quot;: LIGHT_GREEN,
                        &quot;Poverty gap per capita&quot;: DARK_GREEN},
    yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
    yaxis_tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
)
fig.add_hline(1, line_dash=&quot;dot&quot;)
fig.show(config=CONFIG)
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f3() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_3&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button3&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset3&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021/2021-01-18-racial-poverty-disparities-mlk-day-2021-asset-3.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset3&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. King didn’t live to see today’s renaissance of guaranteed income, with pandemic responses including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/stimulus-check-600-2000-dollars-eligibility-2021-1-1/&quot;&gt;generous unconditional cash transfers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://mayorsforagi.org&quot;&gt;mayors across America&lt;/a&gt; calling for pilots, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.express.co.uk/news/politics/1316702/nicola-sturgeon-news-scotland-ubi-Universal-Basic-Income-SNP-latest-economy&quot;&gt;leaders across the world&lt;/a&gt; embracing the idea.
But our analysis validates his intuition and the intertwining of his racial justice and economic justice emphases: guaranteed income will produce not only a less impoverished world, but also a less racially disparate one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:modeling&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Data was gathered from the US Census Bureau’s March Supplement, which covers economic circumstances in 2019. We use the Supplemental Poverty Measure, which incorporates taxes and transfers (including in-kind benefits like SNAP), and adjusts for local housing costs. The flat income tax is applied on positive adjusted gross income. We calculate per-capita poverty gaps by race as the total poverty gap of SPM units with at least one person of that race, divided by the number of people in SPM units with at least one person of that race. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:modeling&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;max&quot;, &quot;connor&quot;, &quot;nate&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="race" />
      
        <category term="poverty" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">$600 per month or more would end one measure of the Black-White poverty disparity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The UBI Center’s 2020 year in review</title>
      <link href="/ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The UBI Center’s 2020 year in review" />
      <published>2021-01-01T07:14:31+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-01T07:14:31+00:00</updated>
      <id>/ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review">&lt;h4 id=&quot;our-work-studies-from-other-researchers-and-the-biggest-ubi-news-from-the-pastyear&quot;&gt;Our work, studies from other researchers, and the biggest UBI news from the past year&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has been a devastating year. Covid-19 has killed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/&quot;&gt;nearly two million people&lt;/a&gt; worldwide, thrown &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/feature/2020/10/07/global-action-urgently-needed-to-halt-historic-threats-to-poverty-reduction&quot;&gt;tens of millions&lt;/a&gt; into extreme poverty, and disrupted virtually every aspect of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has also changed perceptions of social protection programs. With millions unable to work safely, populations are more open to unconditional cash transfers, and governments have delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers have continued to investigate how societies could adopt universal basic income policies, and fueled by our biggest growth year (we now have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubicenter.org/about&quot;&gt;ten researchers&lt;/a&gt;), we’ve contributed with policy simulations and evidence reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following up on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019-48b7db543094&quot;&gt;2019 review&lt;/a&gt;, this post summarizes our work from the past year, along with studies from other researchers and the biggest UBI news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ubi-centerresearch&quot;&gt;UBI Center research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;policy-simulation&quot;&gt;Policy simulation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bread-and-butter simulations of UBI policy became more targeted, robust, and policy-relevant throughout 2020. Our simulations showed how UBI would shrink &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/how-universal-basic-income-would-affect-the-black-white-poverty-and-wealth-gaps-452e2af1497b&quot;&gt;black-white poverty and wealth gaps&lt;/a&gt;, how it would affect &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20200731/ada30.html&quot;&gt;people with disabilities&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201012/indigenous.html&quot;&gt;Indigenous Americans&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201111/veterans.html&quot;&gt;Veterans&lt;/a&gt;, and how a &lt;a href=&quot;http://child-allowance.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;child allowance&lt;/a&gt; would cut child poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-0.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first paper of the Covid era showed how different UBI policy designs could &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/viewer?url=https://raw.githubusercontent.com/UBICenter/covid19/master/UBI_for_Covid_19.pdf&quot;&gt;stabilize the poverty rate&lt;/a&gt; amid income-lowering recessions, and our latest analysis showed how replacing our existing tax code with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201230/us-flat-tax.html&quot;&gt;flat income tax&lt;/a&gt; could be made progressive with a UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-1.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also compared UBI to other policies (given a fixed budget), finding that it would be more progressive than &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201117/student-debt.html&quot;&gt;canceling student debt&lt;/a&gt;, and likely more progressive than expanding additional US &lt;a href=&quot;http://covid.ubicenter.org/fpuc&quot;&gt;unemployment benefits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-research&quot;&gt;Other research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, we expanded our research portfolio beyond policy simulation to other topics related to UBI. We produced &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201214/canada-homelessness-experiment.html&quot;&gt;novel analyses&lt;/a&gt; and context of a cash transfer experiment targeting Canadians experiencing homelessness. To inform Democratic primaries, we &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel-9d53646a3245&quot;&gt;summarized&lt;/a&gt; candidates’ stances on UBI. And we tracked and summarized all 27 emergency cash transfer proposals in the US (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thebalance.com/pandemic-tests-universal-basic-income-5078483&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt; of our tracker in The Balance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-2.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also integrated deeper non-simulation analysis into simulation projects. Our &lt;a href=&quot;http://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/empirical&quot;&gt;child allowance project&lt;/a&gt; summarized dozens of papers on the impacts of child poverty, while our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20201230/us-flat-tax.html#generous-transfers-are-the-key-to-inequality-reduction&quot;&gt;flat tax project&lt;/a&gt; included original statistical analysis of tax and transfer policies associated with inequality reduction among OECD countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-3.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-source-contributions&quot;&gt;Open source contributions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re the first and only economic policy think tank to open-source all of our work, and we take pride in using and contributing to open source software for economic policy research. This year, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.org&quot;&gt;Policy Simulation Library&lt;/a&gt; accepted two of our Python packages — &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.github.io/openfisca-uk&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;microdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;for analyzing survey data, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.github.io/openfisca-uk&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;openfisca-uk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for simulating UK economic policy — to its catalog, adding two of our staff to its leadership council. We also created new incubating models to work with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/scf&quot;&gt;US Survey of Consumer Finances&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nikhilwoodruff/frs&quot;&gt;UK Family Resources Survey&lt;/a&gt;. Our researchers contributed to several open source projects on GitHub, from improving documentation in PSL’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/Tax-Calculator/pull/2420&quot;&gt;Tax-Calculator&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/OG-USA/pull/634&quot;&gt;OG-USA&lt;/a&gt; economic models to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mwburke/stargazer/pull/53&quot;&gt;enhancing&lt;/a&gt; Python’s support for producing publication-grade regression tables. Finally, we made our own research more open and reproducible by moving most content to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyterbook.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter-Book&lt;/a&gt;, which shows hideable code within the interactive web document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;outreach&quot;&gt;Outreach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shared our research in numerous forums: op-eds in The Hill on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/514672-would-basic-income-be-better-than-additional-unemployment-benefits&quot;&gt;unemployment benefit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/opinion/education/529953-child-allowance-would-boost-gdp&quot;&gt;child allowance&lt;/a&gt; analyses; presentations at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1456wwH-W24gXrfOhvDRCHyqZRhelUx64XTrXj-HQRYw/edit#slide=id.g6293382480_0_338&quot;&gt;Tax Economists Forum&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WoHnOqFu6KQ&quot;&gt;PyData Global&lt;/a&gt; conference, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/lL17YLCGSxs&quot;&gt;Social Giving&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MtDjRauJmE8&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wCK_xw0IMDs&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/my-nerds-for-humanity-interview-on-basic-income-6f6a13275b44&quot;&gt;channels&lt;/a&gt;. We also launched our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://us3.campaign-archive.com/home/?u=ffee9994a6979a91e881b8c13&amp;amp;id=938462295c&quot;&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt; and YouTube &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCg0PhP-7kCHtAjcVc7XfTfA&quot;&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;plans-for2021&quot;&gt;Plans for 2021&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2021 promises to be an even bigger year, with upcoming simulations of UBI in the UK, benchmarks of UBI against competing policies, macroeconomic and behavioral effects, interactive tools, events and partnerships, a new website, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;external-research&quot;&gt;External research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reviews-andtools&quot;&gt;Reviews and tools&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/uploads/Umbrella%20Review%20BI_final.pdf&quot;&gt;Stanford Basic Income Lab UBI study cross-synthesis&lt;/a&gt; affirmed that UBI-type programs alleviate poverty, improve health and education outcomes, while having minimal effects on labour market participation. It nominated understanding of the “tradeoffs between UBI and other programs,” and particularly the impact of “financing a UBI through new revenue streams or diversions from existing programs” as a key gap in the existing research — precisely the gap our research aims to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cash transfer evidence base also became more navigable with the creation of new tools to access studies that address the impact of cash transfer. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/&quot;&gt;Basic Income Lab&lt;/a&gt; expanded its platform, providing new &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/research/ubi-visualization/&quot;&gt;visualizations&lt;/a&gt; that allow users to dive into studies related to UBIs categorized by outcome. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/cash-research-explorer/&quot;&gt;Cash Research Explorer&lt;/a&gt; that enables users to filter and sort a large database of existing cash transfer studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;policy-simulations&quot;&gt;Policy simulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcomed not being the only UBI simulators in town, with studies on various policy designs being conducted around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, Columbia University’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.povertycenter.columbia.edu/&quot;&gt;Center on Poverty &amp;amp; Social Policy&lt;/a&gt; released a series of policy briefs on how a guaranteed income would affect poverty, comparing recent policy proposals and addressing child inclusion in a carbon tax and universal dividend program. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/up-front/2020/01/30/how-a-vat-could-tax-the-rich-and-pay-for-universal-basic-income/&quot;&gt;simulation from Brookings&lt;/a&gt; found 10% VAT could reduce the debt by $2.9 trillion over 10 years, boost means-tested programs and Social Security, and provide a UBI at 20% of the poverty line, raising bottom-quintile income by 17%. And a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w27351&quot;&gt;dynamic macro model&lt;/a&gt; found that most Americans would prefer UBI today, but future generations would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1035304620964272&quot;&gt;Australian study&lt;/a&gt; found that an “affluence-tested” UBI would reduce inequality and poverty to levels similar to Nordic welfare states, requiring an increase in taxation to approximately the OECD average. Other simulations in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s41825-017-0007-2&quot;&gt;Gulf states&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://works.bepress.com/widerquist/119/&quot;&gt;the UK&lt;/a&gt; showed similarly egalitarian results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal taxation papers continued to study policies that rebate excess revenue as UBI. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28098&quot;&gt;One such paper&lt;/a&gt; found that optimal tax rates and welfare rise when incorporating uncertainty around labor responses, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w27622&quot;&gt;another from NBER&lt;/a&gt; found that “a uniform flat tax on capital and labor income combined with a lump-sum transfer is nearly optimal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resilience-and-adherence-covid-19&quot;&gt;Resilience and adherence: COVID-19&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a difficult year in which COVID-19 brought economies around the world to a standstill, we learned more about how cash transfers can create resilience to income shocks. The continuation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt;’s UBI experiment in Kenya during the COVID-19 crisis offered the opportunity to estimate the impact of unconditional cash transfers to poor families. As the first true UBI experiment in history — guaranteeing payments that meet basic needs for each member of randomly selected villages for up to 12 years — its first results deserve special attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://econweb.ucsd.edu/~pniehaus/papers/ubi_covid.pdf&quot;&gt;Banerjee et al.&lt;/a&gt; found that the UBI, which began in 2016, significantly reduced recipient hunger, sickness and depression in spite of the pandemic, though with modest effect sizes. It also reduced hospital visits and decreased social interactions, indicating that access to a UBI offered people a greater capacity to follow public health recommendations about social distancing and thereby likely reduced contagion rates. While recipients lost the income gains from starting non-agricultural enterprises during the pandemic, they suffered smaller increases in hunger, indicating that the UBI induced recipients to accept more income risk by mitigating the effects of adverse income shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mental-health&quot;&gt;Mental health&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, numerous studies shed light on how cash transfers can reduce stress, improve self-reported well-being and enable participants to make more rational long-term economic decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finland’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kela.fi/web/en/news-archive/-/asset_publisher/lN08GY2nIrZo/content/results-of-the-basic-income-experiment-small-employment-effects-better-perceived-economic-security-and-mental-wellbeing&quot;&gt;basic income experiment&lt;/a&gt;, which was carried out in 2017–18, reported this year that basic income recipients were more satisfied with their lives, experienced less mental strain and had a more positive perception of their economic welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a developing context, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jae/advance-article/doi/10.1093/jae/ejaa010/6015888&quot;&gt;Molotsky and Handa&lt;/a&gt; found that national cash transfers in Malawi reduced stress and improved positive affect among recipients; these psychological effects directly impacted on economic decision-making, encouraging recipients to make more long term decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28106&quot;&gt;Haushofer et al., 2020b&lt;/a&gt; found that cash transfers in rural Kenya outperformed more costly psychotherapy programs both in economic and psychological well-being outcomes, and that a combination of cash transfers and psychotherapy was no more effective than cash alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0304387818310289?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;Haushofer et al., 2020a&lt;/a&gt; found that in Nairobi, free health insurance outperformed a uniform cash transfer of the same value in reducing self-reported stress and cortisol levels, though the most conservative statistical bounds render the difference statistically insignificant. It found no effect of either program on other economic and health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large-scale &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.happierlivesinstitute.org/uploads/1/0/9/9/109970865/cash_transfer_meta-analysis_working_paper_1.53.pdf&quot;&gt;meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; found that cash transfers improved self-reported subjective well-being and mental health and that the higher the transfer, the greater the impact. Unconditional cash transfers outperformed conditional cash transfers. And a &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6522/eaay0214?rss%253D1=&quot;&gt;review in Science Magazine&lt;/a&gt; found that “cash transfers and broader antipoverty programs reduce depression and anxiety in randomized trials […] poverty experienced in childhood and in utero [results] in impaired cognitive development and adult mental illness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-effects-of-cash-transfers&quot;&gt;Other effects of cash transfers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voluminous literature on cash transfers continued to grow rapidly in 2020. Here are a sample of influential papers from the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w28074/w28074.pdf&quot;&gt;multifaceted intervention&lt;/a&gt; that included a cash transfer for 30 to 40 weeks improved consumption, food security, income, and health for up to a decade. In Mexico, cash transfers &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1uYloKO69ESDXHIU5n-1XmiLK3APrMs0_/view&quot;&gt;halved homicides&lt;/a&gt; on hot days by reducing stress and increasing air conditioning. In Rwanda, cash transfers &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.01749&quot;&gt;outperformed&lt;/a&gt; a USAID workforce readiness program on key outcomes like income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, the 1990s retraction of cash assistance to poor mothers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28077&quot;&gt;worsened child-parent interactions&lt;/a&gt; (the effect was not traced to changes in the mother’s labor supply). The Alaska Permanent Fund Dividend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w26712&quot;&gt;increased fertility&lt;/a&gt; (births per woman) by 13 percent after its introduction, mostly among women aged 20 to 44.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conditionality-and-targeting&quot;&gt;Conditionality and targeting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0305750X20300024#f0010&quot;&gt;New evidence&lt;/a&gt; from the Kenya Cash Transfer Programme for Orphans and Vulnerable Children for at-risk children shows that enforcing compliance with health conditions with monitoring and fines doesn’t improve program effectiveness compared to ‘labelling’ transfers — providing suggestions for how recipients should use transfers. The study also showed that fines had regressive impacts. Among the poorest transfer recipients, fines for noncompliance were associated with a significant decline in non-food consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers also quantified the cost of &lt;a href=&quot;https://wagner.nyu.edu/impact/research/publications/program-recertification-costs-evidence-snap&quot;&gt;administrative burdens&lt;/a&gt; for SNAP recipients in the US, and the New York Times centered this research in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/01/28/upshot/administrative-burden-quiz.html&quot;&gt;interactive story&lt;/a&gt;. The Jain Family Institute published two papers in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jainfamilyinstitute.org/projects/from-idea-to-reality-the-future-of-guaranteed-income/&quot;&gt;series on guaranteed income&lt;/a&gt;, describing implementation of guaranteed income in the US and a framework for considering what programs the guaranteed income could suitably replace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;polls&quot;&gt;Polls&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pollsters asked people from all over the world how they felt about UBI and cash transfers, and the timing of these polls showed how Covid-19 affected sentiments toward the welfare state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first polls came from the US, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheUBICenter/status/1245575691082428423&quot;&gt;in February&lt;/a&gt;, 63% of people aged 18–36 supported a universal basic income of $1,000 per month for adults. Data for Progress &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/2020/3/19/voters-want-the-government-to-send-everyone-1000&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; that net support for sending each American a check for $1,000 rose from -15 to +32 between March 2 and March 17, when the gravity of the pandemic became apparent. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/3/21/voters-support-a-robust-cash-payment&quot;&gt;Also in March&lt;/a&gt;, Data for Progress found that Americans prefer ongoing payments to one-time payments by a 38-point margin, and between monthly payments of (a) $2,000/adult + $1,000/child and (b) $1,000/adult, voters prefer the larger amount by a 15-point margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polls outside the US found majority support for the policy, too. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://eupinions.eu/de/text/in-crisis-europeans-support-radical-positions&quot;&gt;March poll&lt;/a&gt; found that 71% of Europeans support UBI; an &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/5y7qpjzd6v/NEON_CoronavirusClimate_200417_W.pdf&quot;&gt;April poll&lt;/a&gt; found that 51% of Brits supported it; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.probe-research.com/polls/manitobans-support-universal-basic-income-higher-taxes-high-income-earners-and-larger&quot;&gt;also in April&lt;/a&gt;, 62% of Manitoba, Canada residents supported UBI; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/news/2020-12-11/survey-says-most-australians-welcome-universal-basic-income/12970924&quot;&gt;as of October&lt;/a&gt;, 58% of Australians supported it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calls-forubi&quot;&gt;Calls for UBI&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government leaders and other influential people and organizations called for UBI pilots and policies, especially relating to (but not limited to) the Covid-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most forceful voices came from the UK. The Liberal Democrats (the third largest party, which received &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Results_breakdown_of_the_2019_United_Kingdom_general_election&quot;&gt;12 percent of votes&lt;/a&gt; in 2019) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libdems.org.uk/a20-ubi&quot;&gt;endorsed UBI&lt;/a&gt; in September, and in October, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubilabnetwork.org/letter-to-rishi-sunak&quot;&gt;over 500 MPs, peers and councillors&lt;/a&gt; requested that the Chancellor support UBI trials. Throughout the year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/oct/31/covid-job-losses-lead-mps-to-call-for-trials-of-universal-basic-income&quot;&gt;several councils&lt;/a&gt; campaigned to launch UBI pilots in their areas, including Liverpool, Brighton, Leeds, Norwich and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaders in Canada have been similarly enthusiastic. Canada has a rich history of unconditional cash transfers: they created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200624-canadas-forgotten-universal-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;Mincome experiment&lt;/a&gt; in the 1970s, a UBI pilot in the province of Ontario (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/economy/making-sense/ontario-is-canceling-its-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;prematurely cancelled&lt;/a&gt; in 2019), a generous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubiworks.ca/ccb&quot;&gt;child benefit&lt;/a&gt;, and the CERB program providing CAD 2,000 (USD 1,570) per month through September to people who’d lost employment due to Covid-19. In July, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalpost.com/news/politics/now-is-the-time-to-bring-a-basic-income-program-to-canada-says-b-c-senator-but-the-pilot-project-could-cost-100-million&quot;&gt;British Columbia Senator Yuen Pau&lt;/a&gt; Woo suggested testing UBI, and in the same month, the Senate national finance committee released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://sencanada.ca/en/info-page/parl-43-1/nffn-covid-19-relief-in-times-of-crisis/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; highlighting the need for UBI. In September, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2020/09/15/coalition-calls-on-federal-liberals-to-bring-in-a-basic-income-to-address-gender-inequity.html&quot;&gt;a coalition&lt;/a&gt; of nearly 4,000 individuals and organizations called on the federal government to work toward UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, several members of Congress called for one-time and recurring unconditional payments amid Covid-19 (see our &lt;a href=&quot;http://covid19tracker.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;tracker&lt;/a&gt;), including a proposal for $2,000 monthly checks per person from Senator Bernie Sanders and Vice President-elect Kamala Harris. The one-time relief payments of $1,200 from March were renewed at $600 in the December bill, along with flat payments of $300 per week for unemployed people (down from $600 from April through July). The governor of Alaska also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alaskapublic.org/2020/12/14/dunleavy-proposes-nearly-5000-in-dividends-for-alaskans-cuts-other-state-spending/&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; increasing the Alaska Permanent Fund Dividend from its normal value of $1,000-$3,000 to $5,000 due to the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-UBI US voices were elevated in 2021, too. In April, Jack Dorsey created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/recode/2020/4/7/21212757/coronavirus-jack-dorsey-charity-billion-llc&quot;&gt;$1 billion philanthropic fund&lt;/a&gt; from his holdings in Square; the fund has since grown to $3.7 billion, of which he’s spent $330 million, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uT6Tw0lrYMj9YSQpkMAyf_i31Urf0IWW5wIJ76Rckv8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;$44 million&lt;/a&gt; for UBI pilots. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1286675223434141697&quot;&gt;Pro-UBI&lt;/a&gt; Elon Musk became the world’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/sergeiklebnikov/2020/12/08/elon-musk-passes-bernard-arnault-to-become-the-worlds-second-richest-person/?sh=ab0da895cb0d&quot;&gt;second wealthiest person&lt;/a&gt; in December. Andrew Yang, who centered his presidential campaign on UBI (we &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/distributional-analysis-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-d8dab818bf1b&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/a-revenue-neutral-version-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-d7d517dbeeea&quot;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/why-some-low-income-people-come-out-behind-in-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-c95d0f1cc433&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://plans.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;calculator&lt;/a&gt; on his plan in 2019), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/02/11/politics/andrew-yang-ends-2020-presidential-campaign/index.html&quot;&gt;ended his presidential campaign&lt;/a&gt; in February, but he is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/homenews/state-watch/531337-poll-finds-andrew-yang-favored-for-new-york-city-mayor&quot;&gt;now the favorite&lt;/a&gt; for New York City’s 2021 mayoral race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaders in various other countries have supported UBI as well. In March, one of Australia’s largest unions &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-8154513/Australian-union-pushes-universal-income-740-week.html&quot;&gt;called for a guaranteed income&lt;/a&gt; throughout the pandemic, structured as a job guarantee plus AUD 740 (USD 725) per week for people who don’t participate in the job guarantee program. In South Africa, the governing party &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.groundup.org.za/media/uploads/documents/anc_nec_stsc_big-1.pdf&quot;&gt;highlighted&lt;/a&gt; the need for a UBI, but plans for a 2020 policy were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-safrica-economy-universalincomegrant/south-africa-will-not-have-universal-basic-income-grant-this-year-minister-says-idUSKCN24W2WK&quot;&gt;scrapped in July&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, the United Nations &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cepal.org/en/publications/45544-social-challenge-times-covid-19&quot;&gt;Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean&lt;/a&gt; and UN Development Program’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.un.org/en/story/2020/05/1063312&quot;&gt;Asia-Pacific bureau&lt;/a&gt; have called for UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;guaranteed-income-initiatives&quot;&gt;Guaranteed income initiatives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to one-time payments and ongoing payments to unemployed people like those in the US and Canada, several governments and nonprofits are sending regular cash payments to broad sets of people without requiring work history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayorsforagi.org/&quot;&gt;Mayors for a Guaranteed Income&lt;/a&gt; — which now includes over 30 mayors — is driving a number of new philanthropically-funded guaranteed income pilots, including in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2020-10-18/800-compton-residents-to-get&quot;&gt;Compton&lt;/a&gt;, and established the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sp2.upenn.edu/center-for-guaranteed-income-research-recently-launched/&quot;&gt;Center for Guaranteed Income Research&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Pennsylvania. &lt;a href=&quot;https://reason.com/2020/10/13/san-francisco-will-pay-artists-1000-a-month-in-universal-basic-income/&quot;&gt;San Francisco&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincometoday.com/long-beach-moves-ahead-with-guaranteed-basic-income-for-some-artists/&quot;&gt;Long Beach&lt;/a&gt; will also both give basic incomes to artists (see our comments in coverage of the San Francisco program). But the nonprofit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/covid-19/us/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; has already distributed the most — since March, they’ve transferred $1,000 to each of 134,000 SNAP recipients, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/GiveDirectly-End-of-Year-Update.pdf?utm_source=email&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=202012eoyupdatematch&amp;amp;utm_content=eoy_update&quot;&gt;99% efficiency&lt;/a&gt; and an average of two days between enrollment and first payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveDirectly also delivered transfers to over 500,000 recipients outside the US, creating new contact-free payment models and adding new programs. For example, they provided USAID-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.liberianobserver.com/news/givedirectly-educational-stipends-for-12th-graders-writing-the-wassce-exam/&quot;&gt;educational stipends&lt;/a&gt; of $50 to 37,000 12th-graders in every high school in Liberia, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90585079/how-givedirectly-is-finding-the-poorest-people-in-the-world-and-sending-them-cash&quot;&gt;applied machine learning&lt;/a&gt; to identify and pay extremely poor households in Togo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-brazil-economics/brazils-government-backs-new-basic-income-payments-to-poor-idUKKBN26J381&quot;&gt;expanding&lt;/a&gt; its Bolsa Familia cash transfer into a new program called Renda Cidada (“citizen income”), and Bogota, Colombia, is giving cash and food aid to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-world-ahead/2020/11/17/claudia-lopez-on-the-acceleration-of-social-innovation&quot;&gt;over 700,000 households&lt;/a&gt;. Spain introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/economy/2020/5/30/spain-introduces-basic-income-scheme-to-tackle-poverty&quot;&gt;minimum income program&lt;/a&gt; that intended to benefit over 2 million individuals, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/news/spain-struggles-to-put-in-place-basic-income-scheme-01598763004&quot;&gt;implementation challenges&lt;/a&gt; are slowing it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-4.png#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On most measures, 2021 has a low bar to clear to outdo 2020. Given this array of studies, UBI research might not be one of those measures, but we expect even more simulations, randomized controlled trials, meta-analyses, and new programs to inform UBI policy design and how UBI compares to the status quo and alternatives. To follow our research on these fronts, subscribe to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://ubicenter.us3.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=ffee9994a6979a91e881b8c13&amp;amp;id=938462295c&quot;&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt; or follow us on social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!
The UBI Center team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by Max Ghenis, John Walker, and Ankit Dhingra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written on January 1, 2021 by Max Ghenis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@maxghenis/the-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-f788d892a50&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Max Ghenis</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="pilots" />
      
        <category term="external research" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We joined scholars around the world in accelerating UBI research.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Basic income can make switching to a flat income tax progressive</title>
      <link href="/us-flat-tax" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic income can make switching to a flat income tax progressive" />
      <published>2020-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/us-flat-tax</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/us-flat-tax">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current US income tax code taxes different types of incomes at different rates, includes an array of credits and deductions that primarily benefit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-tax-deductions-economists-hate/&quot;&gt;upper and middle class&lt;/a&gt;, and requires Americans to spend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/documents/economy082710.pdf&quot;&gt;billions of hours and dollars&lt;/a&gt; filing taxes each year.
A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/04/06/the-biggest-u-s-tax-breaks/&quot;&gt;2015 Pew survey&lt;/a&gt; found that 66 percent of Republicans and 48 percent of Democrats support completely changing the tax system.
While there are many ways to reform the tax code, a simple way is taxing every dollar at the same rate; this is often called a “flat tax.”
In this paper, we examine the impact of replacing today’s system with a budget-neutral combination of flat income taxes and universal basic incomes (UBIs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;us-flat-tax-simulations&quot;&gt;US flat tax simulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We simulated the effect of replacing the current federal income tax code and employee side payroll tax with a flat tax over a range of rates.
We allocated any excess revenue to a UBI to make each reform budget-neutral, and filled budget shortfalls with a head tax (equal tax amount per person, essentially a negative UBI). &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:modeling&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:modeling&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A flat tax of approximately 18 percent would raise the same amount of revenue as federal income taxes and employee side payroll do today.
Each percentage point of flat tax raises enough revenue to fund a UBI of $360 per year for each adult and child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import pandas as pd
import numpy as np
import plotly.express as px
import plotly.graph_objects as go
import microdf as mdf
import statsmodels.api as sm
import stargazer.stargazer as sg
from pandas_datareader import wb


summary = pd.read_csv(&quot;data/summary.csv&quot;)


BLUE = &quot;#1976D2&quot;
DARK_BLUE = &quot;#1565C0&quot;
LIGHT_BLUE = &quot;#90CAF9&quot;
GRAY = &quot;#BDBDBD&quot;
CONFIG = {&quot;displayModeBar&quot;: False}

def add_ubi_center_watermark(fig, x, y=-0.14):
    fig.add_layout_image(
        dict(
            source=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/UBICenter/blog/master/jb/_static/ubi_center_logo_wide_blue.png&quot;,
            # See https://github.com/plotly/plotly.py/issues/2975.
            # source=&quot;../_static/ubi_center_logo_wide_blue.png&quot;,
            xref=&quot;paper&quot;, yref=&quot;paper&quot;,
            x=x, y=y,
            sizex=0.12, sizey=0.12,
            xanchor=&quot;right&quot;, yanchor=&quot;bottom&quot;
        )
    )

fig = px.line()

fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=summary.flat_tax,
        y=summary.ubi.round(),
        mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;,
        name=&quot;UBI (head tax)&quot;,
        line=dict(color=BLUE, width=2),
    )
)

fig.add_shape(
    type=&quot;line&quot;, line=dict(dash=&quot;dot&quot;, color=&quot;gray&quot;), x0=-1, x1=50, y0=0, y1=0
)

fig.update_xaxes(
    tickangle=0,
    title_text=&quot;Flat tax rate&quot;,
    tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
    title_standoff=25,
    ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
)

fig.update_yaxes(
    title_text=&quot;Budget-neutral annual UBI (head tax)&quot;,
    tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
    tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
    title_standoff=25,
)

fig.update_xaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
fig.update_yaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
fig.update_layout(
    title_text=&quot;Budget-neutral UBI (head tax) by flat tax rate&quot;,
    hoverlabel_align=&quot;right&quot;,
    font_family=&quot;Roboto&quot;,
    title_font_size=20,
)

add_ubi_center_watermark(fig, 0.98)

fig.update_layout(plot_bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;, hovermode=&quot;x&quot;)
fig.update_layout(legend=dict(yanchor=&quot;top&quot;, y=0.99, xanchor=&quot;left&quot;, x=0.8))
fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;)

fig.show(config=CONFIG)
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/us-flat-tax/2020-12-30-us-flat-tax-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replacement would increase the poverty rate by 37 percent, increase the poverty gap (the dollar amount needed to lift everyone above the poverty line) by 23 percent, and increase inequality (as measured by the Gini index of resources per person) by 7 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining current levels of poverty and inequality requires a higher tax rate to raise funds for a UBI.
A 21 percent flat tax, which would give each person $1,200 per year, would maintain the current poverty gap; a rate and poverty gap; a 22 percent tax giving each person about $1,600 per year would maintain the current poverty rate; a 23 percent tax giving each person about $1,900 would maintain current inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher taxes funding more generous UBIs reduce poverty and inequality to a greater degree.
A flat tax of 30 percent would fund a UBI (including children) of nearly $4,500—cutting poverty in half and inequality by 9 percent.
Going up to 50 percent funds a $1,000 monthly UBI, leaving the poverty rate at a tenth of its currently level and cutting inequality by a third.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chart below shows how different flat tax rates up to 50 percent would impact poverty and inequality (the hover function shows the corresponding head tax or UBI for each reform).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
def trace(col, chg_col, name, string, color):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Args:
        col: Column name.
        chg_col: Column name of change.
        name: Name of column for printing.
        string: Formatting of customdata[1].
        color: Line color.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    fig.add_trace(
        go.Scatter(
            x=summary.flat_tax,
            y=summary[chg_col],
            mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;,
            name=name,
            line=dict(color=color, width=2),
            customdata=np.stack((summary.ubi, summary[col]), axis=-1),
            hovertemplate=&quot;&lt;br /&gt;Flat tax: %{x}&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
            + &quot;UBI (head tax): $%{customdata[0]: .0f}&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
            + name
            + &quot;: &quot;
            + string
            + &quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
            + &quot;Percent change: %{y:.0f}%&lt;br /&gt;&quot;,
            marker=dict(size=5),
        )
    )


fig = px.line()
trace(
    &quot;poverty_rate&quot;,
    &quot;change_poverty_rate&quot;,
    &quot;Poverty rate&quot;,
    &quot;%{customdata[1]: .1f}%&quot;,
    DARK_BLUE,
)
trace(
    &quot;poverty_gap_billions&quot;,
    &quot;change_poverty_gap&quot;,
    &quot;Poverty gap&quot;,
    &quot;$%{customdata[1]: .0f}B&quot;,
    LIGHT_BLUE,
)
trace(&quot;gini&quot;, &quot;change_gini&quot;, &quot;Gini index&quot;, &quot;%{customdata[1]}&quot;, GRAY)


fig.update_xaxes(
    tickangle=0,
    title_text=&quot;Flat tax rate&quot;,
    tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
    title_standoff=25,
    ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
    range=[-2, 51],
)

fig.update_yaxes(
    title_text=&quot;Percent change&quot;,
    ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
    title_standoff=25,
    range=[-101, 301],
)

fig.update_xaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
fig.update_yaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
fig.update_layout(
    title_text=(
        &quot;Replacing employee side FICA and federal income taxes with &quot;
        &quot;a flat tax and UBI (head tax)&quot;
    ),
    title_font_size=20,
    hoverlabel_align=&quot;right&quot;,
    font_family=&quot;Roboto&quot;,
)

add_ubi_center_watermark(fig, 1.01)

fig.update_layout(plot_bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;, hovermode=&quot;x&quot;)
fig.update_yaxes(zeroline=True, zerolinewidth=2, zerolinecolor=&quot;black&quot;)
fig.update_layout(legend=dict(yanchor=&quot;top&quot;, y=0.99, xanchor=&quot;left&quot;, x=0.75))

fig.show(config=CONFIG)
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/us-flat-tax/2020-12-30-us-flat-tax-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the point of the flat tax producing a UBI (18 percent), higher rates lead to more Americans benefiting on a net basis.
Replacing today’s taxes on individual income with a 28 percent flat tax would give each person about $3,700 per year, benefiting the majority of Americans.
The share that come out ahead levels off around 60 percent, with flat taxes of 40 percent or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button3&quot; onclick=&quot;f3()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_3&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = px.line()

fig.add_trace(
    go.Scatter(
        x=summary.flat_tax,
        y=summary.percent_better_off,
        mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;,
        name=&quot;&quot;,
        line=dict(color=BLUE, width=2),
        customdata=np.stack(
            (summary.ubi, summary.percent_better_off), axis=-1
        ),
        hovertemplate=&quot;&lt;br /&gt;Flat tax: %{x}&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
        # TODO: Adapt &quot;UBI&quot; vs &quot;head tax&quot; for value.
        + &quot;UBI (head tax): $%{customdata[0]: .0f}&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
        + &quot;Share better off: %{y:.0f}%&lt;br /&gt;&quot;,
        marker=dict(size=5),
    )
)

fig.add_shape(
    type=&quot;line&quot;,
    line=dict(dash=&quot;dot&quot;, color=&quot;gray&quot;),
    x0=-1,
    x1=50,
    y0=50,
    y1=50,
)

fig.update_xaxes(
    tickangle=0,
    title_text=&quot;Flat tax rate&quot;,
    tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
    title_standoff=25,
    ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
)

fig.update_yaxes(
    title_text=&quot;&quot;,
    ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
    tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
    title_standoff=25,
    tickvals=[0, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, 80, 90, 100],
    range=[20, 80],
)

fig.update_xaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
fig.update_yaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
fig.update_layout(
    title_text=(
        &quot;Share of people who gain from switching to a flat tax and &quot;
        &quot;UBI (head tax)&quot;
    ),
    title_font_size=20,
    hoverlabel_align=&quot;right&quot;,
    font_family=&quot;Roboto&quot;,
)

add_ubi_center_watermark(fig, 0.98)

fig.update_layout(plot_bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;, height=600, width=1000, hovermode=&quot;x&quot;)
fig.update_layout(legend=dict(yanchor=&quot;top&quot;, y=0.99, xanchor=&quot;left&quot;, x=0.8))
fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;)

fig.show(config=CONFIG)
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f3() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_3&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button3&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset3&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/us-flat-tax/2020-12-30-us-flat-tax-asset-3.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset3&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generous-transfers-are-the-key-to-inequality-reduction&quot;&gt;Generous transfers are the key to inequality reduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Labor markets don’t explain the unusually high level of inequality in the United States, third only to Chile and Mexico among developed countries.
For example, the US has similar “market income” inequality as France, Germany, and Finland—each with Gini indexes of 0.50 to 0.51, as shown in the right bars of this graph from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/income-inequality&quot;&gt;Our World In Data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//assets/images/inequality-of-incomes-before-and-after-taxes-and-transfers.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s unusual about the US is how little its government reduces inequality through redistribution.
While France, Germany, and Finland reduce inequality by 0.21, 0.22, and 0.24 on the Gini scale, the US only reduces it by 0.12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What mechanisms do these other countries utilize to cut inequality twice as much as the US?
Counterintuitively, it’s not progressive taxation—the US actually has the most progressive tax code in the OECD,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:progressive-tax&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:progressive-tax&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and tax progressivity does not correlate significantly to inequality reduction (if anything the relationship is slightly negative).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:::{admonition,dropdown,tip} Data notes
Data on inequality reduction comes from Our World In Data’s analysis of OECD data reflecting the period 2012 to 2014.
Data on the concentration index and income shares of household taxes and cash transfers come from Table 4.6 of the OECD’s 2008 report, &lt;a href=&quot;https://read.oecd-ilibrary.org/social-issues-migration-health/growing-unequal_9789264044197-en#page109&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Growing Unequal?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which uses data from around 2005.
Country population is as of 2014 from the World Bank.
Taxes include income taxes and employee social security contributions, not consumption taxes;
however, per &lt;a href=&quot;https://read.oecd-ilibrary.org/social-issues-migration-health/growing-unequal_9789264044197-en#page296&quot;&gt;Figure 11.2&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Growing Unequal?&lt;/em&gt;, consumption taxes have a small effect on relative levels of inequality across OECD countries.
:::&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button4&quot; onclick=&quot;f4()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_4&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
# Get data.
pop = wb.download(indicator=&quot;SP.POP.TOTL&quot;,
                  country='all', start=2014, 
                  end=2014).reset_index().drop('year', axis=1)
pop.rename({&quot;SP.POP.TOTL&quot;: &quot;population&quot;}, axis=1, inplace=True)
# Align countries with Our World In Data and current convention.
pop.country.replace({&quot;Czech Republic&quot;: &quot;Czech Rep.&quot;,
                     &quot;Slovak Republic&quot;: &quot;Slovakia&quot;,
                     &quot;Korea, Rep.&quot;: &quot;South Korea&quot;},
                     inplace=True)

oecd_raw = pd.read_csv(&quot;data/oecd_growing_unequal_2008_table_4_6.csv&quot;)
# Align countries with Our World In Data and current convention.
oecd_raw.country.replace({&quot;Korea&quot;: &quot;South Korea&quot;,
                          &quot;Slovak Rep.&quot;: &quot;Slovakia&quot;},
                         inplace=True)
owid = pd.read_csv(&quot;data/inequality_pre_post_redistribution.csv&quot;)
owid[&quot;gini_diff&quot;] = owid.gini_market - owid.gini_disposable
oecd = oecd_raw.merge(owid, on=&quot;country&quot;).merge(pop, on=&quot;country&quot;)
oecd[&quot;sqrt_pop&quot;] = np.sqrt(oecd.population)

LABELS = {&quot;gini_diff&quot;:
          &quot;Gini reduction via taxes and transfers&quot;,
          &quot;household_taxes_concentration&quot;:
          &quot;Household tax concentration index&quot;,
          &quot;public_cash_transfers_income_share&quot;:
          &quot;Cash transfer share of household income&quot;,
          &quot;population&quot;:
          &quot;Population&quot;,
          &quot;household_taxes_income_share&quot;:
          &quot;Tax share of household income&quot;
         }

# Make plot.
def ineq_scatter(x, xtitle, title, logo_x=1):
    fig = px.scatter(oecd, x=x, y=&quot;gini_diff&quot;, hover_name=&quot;country&quot;,
                     size=&quot;sqrt_pop&quot;, #trendline=&quot;ols&quot;,
                     labels=LABELS,
                     size_max=30)
    # Remove sqrt_pop from hover template.
    hovertemplate = (&quot;&lt;b&gt;%{hovertext}&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&quot; +
                     LABELS[x] + &quot;=%{x}&lt;br /&gt;&quot;
                     &quot;Gini reduction via taxes and transfers=%{y}&quot;)
    fig.update_traces(hovertemplate=hovertemplate)
    fig.update_layout(
        title_text=title,
        title_font_size=20,
        font_family=&quot;Roboto&quot;,
    )

    fig.update_xaxes(
        tickangle=0,
        title_text=xtitle,
        tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
        title_standoff=25,
        ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
        tickprefix=&quot;&quot;,
    )

    fig.update_yaxes(
        title_text=&quot;Difference between market and disposable income Gini index&quot;,
        ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
        tickfont={&quot;size&quot;: 14},
        title_standoff=25,
    )
    if x == &quot;public_cash_transfers_income_share&quot;:
        fig.update_xaxes(ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;)

    fig.update_xaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))
    fig.update_yaxes(title_font=dict(size=16, color=&quot;black&quot;))

    add_ubi_center_watermark(fig, x=logo_x, y=-0.17)

    fig.update_layout(plot_bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;)

    return fig
    
fig = ineq_scatter(x=&quot;household_taxes_concentration&quot;,
             xtitle=&quot;Household tax concentration index&quot;,
             title=&quot;Tax progressivity and inequality reduction in the OECD&quot;)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f4() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_4&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button4&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset4&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/us-flat-tax/2020-12-30-us-flat-tax-asset-4.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset4&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stronger correlate of inequality reduction is the generosity of public cash transfers.
The countries that distribute a higher share of household income as cash transfers generally cut inequality more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button5&quot; onclick=&quot;f5()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_5&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
fig = ineq_scatter(x=&quot;public_cash_transfers_income_share&quot;,
             xtitle=&quot;Public cash transfers / household disposable income&quot;,
             title=&quot;Cash transfer generosity and inequality reduction in the OECD&quot;,
             logo_x=0.95)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f5() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_5&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button5&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset5&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/us-flat-tax/2020-12-30-us-flat-tax-asset-5.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset5&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While overall tax levels also significantly correlate with inequality reduction, the effect vanishes when controlling for cash transfers, as shown in column 4 of the regression table below.
Cash transfers are consistently the dominant predictor of the extent to which governments reduce inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button6&quot; onclick=&quot;f6()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_6&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
oecd = sm.add_constant(oecd)

def gini_reg(x, weighted=True):
    if weighted:
        m = sm.WLS(oecd.gini_diff, oecd[x + [&quot;const&quot;]], oecd.population)
    else:
        m = sm.WLS(oecd.gini_diff, oecd[x + [&quot;const&quot;]])
    return m.fit(cov_type=&quot;HC1&quot;)  # Robust standard errors.

cash_m = gini_reg([&quot;public_cash_transfers_income_share&quot;])
tax_prog_m = gini_reg([&quot;household_taxes_concentration&quot;])
tax_level_m = gini_reg([&quot;household_taxes_income_share&quot;])
combined_m = gini_reg([&quot;household_taxes_concentration&quot;,
                       &quot;household_taxes_income_share&quot;,
                       &quot;public_cash_transfers_income_share&quot;])

def starg(models, covariate_order=None):
    &quot;&quot;&quot; Creates formatted Stargazer object.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    star = sg.Stargazer(models)
    if covariate_order is not None:
        star.covariate_order(covariate_order)
    star.rename_covariates(LABELS)
    star.show_adj_r2 = False
    star.show_residual_std_err = False
    star.show_f_statistic = False
    return star


star = starg([cash_m, tax_level_m, tax_prog_m, combined_m],
             [&quot;public_cash_transfers_income_share&quot;,
              &quot;household_taxes_income_share&quot;,
              &quot;household_taxes_concentration&quot;,
              ])
star.add_custom_notes([&quot;Weighted by population. Robust SEs.&quot;])
star.title(&quot;Inequality reduction and tax levels, tax progressivity, and cash &quot;
           &quot;transfers&quot;)
star
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f6() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_6&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button6&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset6&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/us-flat-tax/2020-12-30-us-flat-tax-asset-6.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset6&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cross-country picture aligns with our simulations: larger UBIs cut inequality more, and even if the tax system that funds those larger UBIs isn’t progressive, ability to fund the UBI is what matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond their simplicity, flat taxes have a number of theoretical advantages.
Progressive tax structures necessarily encourage shifting income from one year to the next as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/105th-congress-1997-1998/reports/marriage.pdf&quot;&gt;marriage, divorce, or both&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:marriage&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:marriage&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Flat taxes treat income neutrally, regardless of when it was earned, by whom, or earners’ family choices.
And because they align marginal tax rates (which determine labor incentives) with effective tax rates (which determine revenue), they raise revenue with relatively little work disincentive.
For example, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w27622&quot;&gt;2020 paper&lt;/a&gt; from the National Bureau of Economic Research found that “a uniform flat tax on capital and labor income combined with a lump-sum transfer is nearly optimal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And consider a progressive tax policy with two rates: 0% (a standard deduction) and 50%.
If the standard deduction is $30,000, the first couple has a total tax liability of $15,000 if filing as a couple, but $0 if filing separately—a large marriage bonus (the second couple’s tax liability is $15,000 whether married or separate).
If the standard deduction instead varies with marital status, e.g. $15,000 for singles and $30,000 for couples, then the first couple will be treated neutrally, paying $15,000 whether filing separate or married.
But now the second couple faces a marriage &lt;em&gt;bonus&lt;/em&gt;, paying $22,500 in taxes if filing separately, but only $15,000  if married.
This can be partly remedied by moving to an individualized tax system, as the United Kingdom does, where earnings are taxed independently of a spouse’s earnings.
But couples will still have joint assets, and therefore face marriage penalties or bonuses on their capital income if capital income is taxed progressively.
Only a flat tax avoids marriage penalties or bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our simulations and cross-country comparisons show that these advantages don’t need to come at the cost of progressivity; if anything, they may enhance progressivity.
Even a 30 percent flat income tax, with excess revenue distributed as UBI, could cut poverty in half, reduce inequality by 10 percent, and leave most Americans better off.
To achieve the egalitarianism of other developed countries, the US should focus less on progressive taxation, and more on how to raise enough revenue to distribute it broadly, effectively, and generously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:modeling&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We replaced all elements of the personal income tax code, including refundable tax credits, but we retained benefit programs. The analysis is fully static; we did not model changes to labor supply resulting from the changes to marginal tax rates and incomes. We used the Current Population Survey (CPS) March Supplement reflecting income from 2019. The Census Bureau estimates tax liabilities using a microsimulation model, but income and taxes are known to be under-reported in the CPS. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:modeling&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:progressive-tax&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As of 2005, the US had the most progressive tax code of any OECD country according to the concentration index (as shown in the graph), as well as two alternative measures: the ratio of concentration coefficients of household taxes to the Gini index of market income, and the ratio of the richest decile’s tax share to its market income share (&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.oecd-ilibrary.org/social-issues-migration-health/growing-unequal_9789264044197-en#page108&quot;&gt;Table 4.5&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Growing Unequal?&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:progressive-tax&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:marriage&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Consider, for example, two couples: one with $30,000 earnings each, and another with one earning $60,000 and the spouse earning $0. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:marriage&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;nate&quot;, &quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="tax" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Flat tax rates of 25 percent or more would reduce poverty and inequality.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What a Canadian experiment tells us about cash transfers and homelessness</title>
      <link href="/canada-homelessness-experiment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What a Canadian experiment tells us about cash transfers and homelessness" />
      <published>2020-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/canada-homelessness-experiment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/canada-homelessness-experiment">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://homelesshub.ca/sites/default/files/SOHC16_final_20Oct2016.pdf&quot;&gt;35,000 Canadians&lt;/a&gt; experience homelessness each night, violating their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/Housing/Pages/Homelessnessandhumanrights.aspx&quot;&gt;right to adequate housing&lt;/a&gt; and threatening their &lt;a href=&quot;https://depts.washington.edu/triolive/quest/2007/TTQ07033/effects.html#:~:text=Their%20health%20gets%20worse%20from,Cardio%2DRespiratory%20diseases&quot;&gt;health, safety&lt;/a&gt; and access to &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.3102/0013189X12468210?casa_token=YsJRZhavl9EAAAAA:iKO6XaWu6oNbDgcRzw3Tml-_m6mHEYmRWGY48rzXTStFpmBEWzqa1L_euQoV8WXYkrwZ8vxj-KGMGQ&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;. The Covid-19 pandemic exacerbates the issue, given &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7206983/&quot;&gt;crowded living conditions and comorbidities&lt;/a&gt;, and the Canadian government has taken new steps to address it, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/article-could-shelter-hotels-be-a-model-for-addressing-homelessness/&quot;&gt;moving people experiencing homelessness into hotels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the pandemic, a Vancouver nonprofit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://forsocialchange.org/&quot;&gt;Foundations for Social Change&lt;/a&gt;, worked with the University of British Columbia to test a novel homelessness intervention: &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5f07a92f21d34b403c788e05/t/5f751297fcfe7968a6a957a8/1601507995038/2020_09_30_FSC_Statement_of_Impact_w_Expansion.pdf&quot;&gt;unconditional cash transfers&lt;/a&gt;. In spring 2018, their &lt;a href=&quot;https://forsocialchange.org/new-leaf-project-overview&quot;&gt;New Leaf Project&lt;/a&gt; (NLP) granted a lump sum cash transfer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britishcolumbia.ca/invest/communities/british-columbia/lower-mainland-southwest/&quot;&gt;Lower Mainland&lt;/a&gt; residents experiencing homelessness, and compared their outcomes to a control group. While some questions remain, the findings reveal that unconditional cash transfers, which are otherwise shown to improve &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cochranelibrary.com/cdsr/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD011135.pub2/full&quot;&gt;health&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1570677X18303575&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;, and other outcomes, offer potential to reduce homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;study-overview&quot;&gt;Study overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NLP selected 115 long-term residents or citizens of Canada aged 19 to 64 who had experienced homelessness within the previous six months. This group is fairly representative of Canada’s homeless population, given only about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homelesshub.ca/about-homelessness/homelessness-101/how-many-people-are-homeless-canada&quot;&gt;10 percent&lt;/a&gt; of people experiencing homelessness in a year were homeless for more than a month, and about &lt;a href=&quot;https://homelesshub.ca/sites/default/files/SOHC16_final_20Oct2016.pdf&quot;&gt;four percent&lt;/a&gt; are aged 65 or older. People with severe substance abuse or mental health disorders were ineligible for NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the experiment, NLP deposited CAD 7,500&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cad&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cad&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; into the bank accounts of 50 participants, randomly selected from the full group of 115. Each cash recipient was also provided access to workshops, and 25 also had access to coaching. Of the 65 who did not receive cash, 19 were provided access to workshops and coaching, while the other 46 were not.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:unbalanced&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:unbalanced&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Workshops focused on the development of a personal financial plan and self-affirmation exercises, and the coaching was offered for six months, aiming to develop and sustain life skills and strategies. Researchers tracked participants over twelve months, filling out questionnaires at one, three, six, nine and twelve months and open-ended qualitative interviews at six and twelve months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import pandas as pd
import plotly.express as px

design = pd.DataFrame(
    {
        &quot;Workshop&quot;: [25, 0],
        &quot;Workshop + coaching&quot;: [25, 19],
        &quot;Neither&quot;: [0, 46]
    },
    index=[&quot;Cash&quot;, &quot;No cash&quot;],
)
design
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/canada-homelessness-experiment/2020-12-14-canada-homelessness-experiment-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spending&quot;&gt;Spending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cash group spent an average of CAD 426 per month more than the non cash group over the course of the year. This amounts to 42 percent more than the non-cash group, or 6 percent of the total CAD 7,500 lump sum transfer. This extra spending covered a diverse range of categories: 54 percent more on transit, 113 percent more on clothing, 34 percent more on food, and so on. Of the treatment groups, the cash group increased its expenditure on alcohol, drugs, and cigarettes by the smallest proportion (11 percent).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:alcohol&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:alcohol&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It also increased its expenditure on food and clothing for the children of recipients by the largest proportion (171 percent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
# Construct data from report.
raw = pd.read_csv(&quot;new_leaf_homeless_expenditures.csv&quot;)
raw.set_index('spending_category', inplace=True)
# Sum food and clothing categories.
food_clothes_kids = raw.loc[['Food for kids', 'Clothes for kids']].sum()
food_clothes_self = raw.loc[['Food', 'Clothes']].sum()
spending = raw.drop([&quot;Food&quot;, &quot;Clothes&quot;, &quot;Food for kids&quot;, &quot;Clothes for kids&quot;])
spending.loc[&quot;Food and clothes for self&quot;] = food_clothes_self
spending.loc[&quot;Food and clothes for kids&quot;] = food_clothes_kids

# Add total row and label total for graph.
spending.loc['TOTAL'] = spending.sum()
spending['is_total'] = spending.index == 'TOTAL'

spending.index.rename('Category', inplace=True)
spending['% difference'] = (
    100 * (spending.cash / spending.non_cash - 1)).round()


import plotly.graph_objects as go

# Plot % difference.
BLUE = '#1976D2'
DARK_BLUE = '#0D47A1'
COLOR_MAP = {True: DARK_BLUE, False: BLUE}  # Total vs non-total.
spending_order = spending.sort_values('% difference')
spending_order.rename({'cash': 'Cash', 'non_cash': 'Non-cash',
                       'is_total': 'Total'},
                      axis=1, inplace=True)
fig = px.bar(spending_order, y=spending_order.index, x='% difference',
             color='Total', color_discrete_map=COLOR_MAP,
             orientation='h', hover_data=['Cash', 'Non-cash'])

fig.update_layout(font=dict(family='Roboto'),
                  plot_bgcolor='white',
                  paper_bgcolor='white',
                  showlegend=False,
                  xaxis_title='Difference between cash and non-cash group',
                  yaxis_title='',
                  xaxis_ticksuffix='%',
                  yaxis={'categoryorder': 'array',
                         'categoryarray': spending_order.index},
                  title='Spending differences between cash and non-cash groups'
                  )
fig.add_layout_image(
    dict(
        source=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/UBICenter/blog/master/jb/_static/ubi_center_logo_wide_blue.png&quot;,
        # See https://github.com/plotly/plotly.py/issues/2975.
        # source=&quot;../_static/ubi_center_logo_wide_blue.png&quot;,
        xref=&quot;paper&quot;, yref=&quot;paper&quot;,
        x=1.04, y=-0.13,
        sizex=0.12, sizey=0.12,
        xanchor=&quot;right&quot;, yanchor=&quot;bottom&quot;
    )
)
fig.show(config={'displayModeBar': False})
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/canada-homelessness-experiment/2020-12-14-canada-homelessness-experiment-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of quantifying the changes is as a share of spending. Alcohol, drugs, and cigarettes made up 9 percent of the cash group’s spending, a fifth less than the non-cash group’s 11.4 percent, while food and clothes for children made up 7.9 percent of the cash group’s spending, nearly double the 4.1 percent share in the non-cash group. The cash group also spent a larger share on clothes (for themselves) and transit, and a smaller share on rent and food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transitions-to-stable-housing&quot;&gt;Transitions to stable housing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cash recipients also spent less time homeless than the control group. The two groups started similarly, but in the month following the intervention, the cash group was only homeless for 49 percent of days, while the control group was homeless for 78 percent of those days. The effect diminished over time, and by the end of the year, the two groups converged at around a fifth of days homeless. Overall, people in the cash group spent an average of 88 fewer days homeless throughout the full year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/days_homeless_chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Days homeless fell faster over the year for the cash group than the non-cash group&quot; title=&quot;Change in days homeless for cash and non-cash groups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those extra 88 days in homelessness housing and services would have cost the government about $8,200, exceeding the $7,500 grant (NLP did not report total costs beyond the grant, which would factor into a comprehensive cost-effectiveness analysis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In open-ended surveys, cash recipients reported that they did not have to depend on social services and could move into housing that better met their preferences. For instance, one participant said, “The impact it had on my life was huge. I was able to do a lot of things that I couldn’t do before. It has changed my ability to make proper choices. If I had not received the cash transfer, I wouldn’t be able to move out. Wouldn’t be able to get my car back on the road. None of that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparison-with-other-studies&quot;&gt;Comparison with other studies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While NLP is the first randomized controlled trial giving unconditional cash transfers to people experiencing homelessness, it aligns with other studies on how cash transfers are spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diversity of NLP participants’ spending is not unusual. The NGO GiveDirectly, which distributes unconditional cash transfers to extremely poor households in East Africa, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article/131/4/1973/2468874?casa_token=r0_EGO-olVkAAAAA:D-gM7NEQ05yqBPV7qpwoDUZdQYeBkc0k0VD25VTBNDC9UAJbhM12Z45LDcGE3YRDELaGfBD7ktbJjA&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; in a randomized controlled trial that “With the exception of temptation goods (alcohol and tobacco), transfers increase expenditures in all categories, including food, medical and education expenditure, and social events.” GiveDirectly’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GDLive tool&lt;/a&gt; shows unfiltered, unedited stories from recipients of their unconditional cash transfers and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/ubi-study&quot;&gt;universal basic income&lt;/a&gt; payments; perusing the stories of UBI recipients reveals variety in spending, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/1b0ed686-5aef-4386-8fc3-0c00078d810d/199799?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;poultry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/a048e9ee-4ee3-4af4-9a95-3e3a64b2d568/199175?context=search-UBI#payment_23&quot;&gt;tea seedlings&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/6e54ba92-ddde-4634-8c8e-f092303c56e6/199793?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;school fees&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/65e70a79-f575-49e4-82e4-88bcf186e395/199033?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;dowries&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/cf2ec5ca-0fa8-4cab-98ed-3b8712ccf0e9/199064?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;water tanks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/822e173e-d163-4472-a6ac-5124a59f44d1/199001?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;homebuilding materials&lt;/a&gt;. A study of Australia’s Covid-19 economic support payment also found that recipients—mostly pensioners—increased spending across a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smh.com.au/business/the-economy/groceries-vs-video-games-how-women-and-men-spend-their-stimulus-payments-differently-20200419-p54l88.html&quot;&gt;diverse range of categories&lt;/a&gt;. Given many in-kind assistance programs target just one or two categories each, such as food and rent, cash can fill in gaps for other needs that might be harder for policymakers to anticipate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending on children is especially common, as evidenced by the robust evidence that cash transfers benefit children. As we summarize in &lt;a href=&quot;https://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/empirical.html&quot;&gt;our child allowance paper&lt;/a&gt;, cash transfers consistently improve education and nutrition, as well as long-term outcomes like earnings and even lifespan, across both developing and developed countries. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w14624/w14624.pdf&quot;&gt;One study&lt;/a&gt; from Canada found that when Manitoba increased its child benefit in 2001, children ages 0 to 3 showed improved motor and social development, children ages 4-5 showed lower aggression and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common concern around giving money to poor people is that they will spend on temptation goods like alcohol, drugs, and cigarettes. This worry motivated San Francisco voters to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_Proposition_N_(2002)&quot;&gt;replace cash assistance&lt;/a&gt; for people experiencing homelessness with in-kind benefits like housing, in a 2002 program called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/politics/la-pol-ca-gavin-newsom-homelessness-san-francisco-20181023-story.html&quot;&gt;“Care Not Cash.”&lt;/a&gt; A number of studies show such concerns to be misplaced. Data from San Francisco’s pre-Care-Not-Cash days indicates that homeless cash recipients were &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1093/jurban/jti015&quot;&gt;less likely to use drugs&lt;/a&gt; than those who didn’t receive cash (they were also less likely to receive income from selling drugs or be incarcerated, and more likely to find shelter). A &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/184358/drinking-highest-among-educated-upper-income-americans.aspx&quot;&gt;2015 Gallup poll&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3185179/&quot;&gt;2011 analysis&lt;/a&gt; of the Panel Study of Income Dynamics also found that low-income people consume less alcohol than higher-income people (though they’re more likely to drink heavy quantities and similarly likely to report that they drink more than they should). A &lt;a href=&quot;http://documents1.worldbank.org/curated/en/617631468001808739/pdf/WPS6886.pdf&quot;&gt;2014 World Bank meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; demonstrates that these results are not mere correlations: data from 19 quantitative papers, including several randomized controlled trials, found that cash transfers most often &lt;em&gt;reduced&lt;/em&gt; or had no effect on temptation good consumption.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:temptation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:temptation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada has long welcomed unconditional cash transfers, from the 1970s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200624-canadas-forgotten-universal-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;“Mincome” program&lt;/a&gt; in Manitoba to its unusually generous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/services/child-family-benefits/canada-child-benefit-overview.html&quot;&gt;child benefit&lt;/a&gt; to its prematurely-cancelled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/economy/making-sense/ontario-is-canceling-its-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;basic income pilot&lt;/a&gt; in Ontario. And as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/development/desa/dspd/wp-content/uploads/sites/22/2019/05/CASEY_Louise_Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;developed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/development/desa/dspd/wp-content/uploads/sites/22/2019/05/SPEAK_Suzanne_Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; countries tackle homelessness, discussions inevitably include cash, whether it’s San Francisco &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_Proposition_N_(2002)&quot;&gt;retracting cash assistance&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 or Manila introducing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-81-322-2160-9_15&quot;&gt;conditional cash transfer&lt;/a&gt; in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NLP unites Canadian interest in cash transfers with homelessness research. It shows that people experiencing homelessness spread lump-sum transfers over time and across spending categories—especially focusing on their children—and that cash transfers accelerate transitions into stable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions following this study remain. For example, how would cash transfers affect the &lt;a href=&quot;https://canadiancentreforaddictions.org/addiction-in-the-homeless-population/&quot;&gt;40 percent&lt;/a&gt; of Canadians experiencing homelessness who have substance abuse disorders? Or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lop.parl.ca/staticfiles/PublicWebsite/Home/ResearchPublications/InBriefs/PDF/2014-11-e.pdf&quot;&gt;similar share&lt;/a&gt; with mental illness? NLP excluded both groups from this round, though a &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6522/eaay0214&quot;&gt;recent Science meta-review&lt;/a&gt; found that “cash transfers and broader anti-poverty programs reduce depression and anxiety in randomized trials.” The long-term effects on children experiencing homelessness may be even starker, as the review also finds that “poverty experienced in childhood and in utero [results] in impaired cognitive development and adult mental illness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question is: how do lump sum transfers, as used in the NLP experiment, compare to recurring payments for people experiencing homelessness? Research to date on this question has largely focused on developing countries. For example, a review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.odi.org/sites/odi.org.uk/files/odi-assets/publications-opinion-files/5745.pdf&quot;&gt;post-emergency aid and development&lt;/a&gt; contexts suggests that regular payments are less prone to corruption than lump sum transfers, and that they outperform on measures of social protection, while lump-sum transfers can more effectively spur investment if targeted to entrepreneurs. Similarly, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article/131/4/1973/2468874?casa_token=r0_EGO-olVkAAAAA:D-gM7NEQ05yqBPV7qpwoDUZdQYeBkc0k0VD25VTBNDC9UAJbhM12Z45LDcGE3YRDELaGfBD7ktbJjA&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly study&lt;/a&gt; among poor households in rural Kenya found: “Monthly transfers are more likely than lump-sum transfers to improve food security, whereas lump-sum transfers are more likely to be spent on durables,” and forthcoming results from its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/ubi-study/&quot;&gt;basic income experiment&lt;/a&gt; will shed more light on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond helping people currently experiencing homelessness, how can cash transfers prevent homelessness? Studies from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-ucla-anderson-forecast-20180613-story.html&quot;&gt;UCLA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zillow.com/research/homelessness-rent-affordability-22247/&quot;&gt;Zillow&lt;/a&gt; link housing affordability and homelessness, suggesting that (along with reducing housing costs) raising incomes via cash transfers could keep people housed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally: how much of these effects can be attributed to cash transfers compared to coaching, workshops, and other overhead, and how do these other costs affect cost-benefit analysis? This first experimental design makes it difficult to disentangle effects, but future experiments could omit other components to focus on the cash transfer, or test other components in a grid or hierarchical design. For example, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28106&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt; on psychological well-being in rural Kenya employed a two-by-two experimental design to study the effect of cash transfers, a psychotherapy program, and the combination of the two. This revealed that, while the cash transfer improved well-being, psychotherapy did not—either by itself or in conjunction with the cash. A similar approach could quantify the effect of coaching or workshops, conditional on cash transfers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundations for Social Change has committed to publishing a peer-reviewed paper on this round of results, and they are raising $10 million to enroll more participants across more Canadian cities and expand research capacity. Any follow-up research is likely to improve the precision of these estimates on expenditures and housing stability, and quantify the external validity to new contexts, even if only geographic. Open questions on cash and homelessness makes this fertile ground for further research, whether from NLP or other organizations. If nothing else, this study suggests that expanding cash assistance will increase spending on diverse needs—especially of children—and accelerate transitions to stable housing, thereby improving the range of outcomes associated with homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cad&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;CAD 7,500 is equivalent to about USD 5,900 as of December 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cad&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:unbalanced&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Researchers did not explain their choice to have unbalanced treatment and control groups, or to give workshop access only to the cash group. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:unbalanced&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:alcohol&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5f07a92f21d34b403c788e05/t/5f751297fcfe7968a6a957a8/1601507995038/2020_09_30_FSC_Statement_of_Impact_w_Expansion.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; claims a “39% reduction in spending on alcohol, cigarettes and drugs.” In email correspondence, Foundations for Social Change clarified that this is a comparison of pre-pilot spending with that at the end of 12 months for the cash group (i.e. not compared to the non-cash group). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:alcohol&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:temptation&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Temptation goods are defined as: “goods that generate positive utility for the self that consumes them, but not for any previous self that anticipates that they will be consumed in the future.” But the meta study focuses principally on alcohol and tobacco. Similarly, the study suggests that temptation goods are synonymous with demerit goods or, “goods that were so demeritorious (either to the consumer or to others) that the government may be correct in regulating their use. That term is sometimes used in reference to alcohol and tobacco in cash transfer studies.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:temptation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;charles&quot;, &quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="canada" />
      
        <category term="homelessness" />
      
        <category term="pilots" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Recipients spent mostly on their children and stable housing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A $300-per-month UBI would cut Veteran poverty in half</title>
      <link href="/veterans" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A $300-per-month UBI would cut Veteran poverty in half" />
      <published>2020-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/veterans</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/veterans">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we honor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/vetdata/veteran_population.asp&quot;&gt;over 19 million Americans&lt;/a&gt; who have served in the military, of whom one in 13 is in poverty. This is a third lower than the poverty rate among non-Veterans, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/12/09/veteran-households-in-u-s-are-economically-better-off-than-those-of-non-veterans/&quot;&gt;higher incomes&lt;/a&gt; and Veteran benefits, but still amounts to over 1.4 million people who lack resources to cover basic needs. Universal basic income would help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Existing assistance programs cut Veteran poverty substantially. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbpp.org/blog/veterans-and-the-safety-net-0&quot;&gt;Two million Veterans&lt;/a&gt; receive refundable tax credits—the Earned Income Tax Credit and the refundable portion of the Child Tax Credit—and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbpp.org/research/food-assistance/snap-helps-13-million-low-income-veterans-including-thousands-in-every&quot;&gt;1.3 million&lt;/a&gt; receive SNAP (formerly food stamps). Certain veteran households are also eligible to receive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/pension/veterans-pension-rates/&quot;&gt;up to $36,387&lt;/a&gt; per year through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/pension/eligibility/&quot;&gt;Veterans Pension&lt;/a&gt; program, depending on their household size, income, net worth, age, service period, and disability status. Veterans with disabilities related to their active-duty service can also receive up to $44,208 per year, depending on their household size and severity of their disability through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/disability/compensation-rates/veteran-rates/&quot;&gt;Veterans Disability Compensation&lt;/a&gt; program. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://benefits.va.gov/benefits/&quot;&gt;Veterans Benefit Administration&lt;/a&gt; provides a number of other benefits around health, education, and other areas, especially for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benefits.va.gov/persona/veteran-elderly.asp&quot;&gt;elderly Veterans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet these programs fail to reach all Veterans in need. As the Department of Veterans Affairs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/vetdata/docs/specialreports/veteran_poverty_trends.pdf&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; in 2012, veterans with disabilities have a higher official poverty rate than non-veterans with disabilities for all age groups except over age 65, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/vetdata/docs/Quickfacts/VA_Utilization_Profile_2017.pdf&quot;&gt;half of Veterans&lt;/a&gt; don’t use VA programs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/opub/ted/2016/43-point-3-percent-of-veterans-with-a-service-connected-disability-were-employed-in-august-2015.htm#:~:text=Bureau%20of%20Labor%20Statistics,-The%20Economics%20Daily&amp;amp;text=In%20August%202015%2C%20about%204.3,all%20veterans%20was%2047.8%20percent.&quot;&gt;20 percent of Veterans&lt;/a&gt; have a service-connected disability, and as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ubicenter.org/20200731/ada30.html&quot;&gt;wrote in July&lt;/a&gt;, one in five people with disabilities is in poverty—nearly double the rate of people without disabilities. In that analysis, we also showed that a $300-per-month universal basic income (UBI) would halve poverty among people with disabilities. What would UBI do for all Veterans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this analysis, we modeled a UBI funded by a flat tax on adjusted gross income (AGI). In this model, every $100 monthly UBI requires a 3.3 percent tax on AGI. To fund a $300-per-month UBI, the federal government would have to levy a 9.8 percent tax. But like we found in the disability analysis, this would also reduce Veteran poverty by half. Poverty among children in Veteran households would be cut by 60 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
# Import Libraries
import microdf as mdf
import numpy as np
import pandas as pd
import plotly.express as px

# Import data
raw = pd.read_csv(&quot;https://github.com/UBICenter/Veteran-s_Day/raw/main/VeteranData.gz&quot;)

# Create Demographic Columns
person = raw.copy(deep=True)
person.columns = person.columns.str.lower()
person[&quot;child&quot;] = person.age &amp;lt; 18
person[&quot;adult&quot;] = person.age &amp;gt;= 18
person[&quot;veteran&quot;] = (person.vetstat == 2) &amp;amp; person.adult
person[&quot;non_veteran&quot;] = (person.vetstat == 1) &amp;amp; person.adult

veterans = person.groupby([&quot;spmfamunit&quot;])[[&quot;veteran&quot;]].sum()
veterans.columns = [&quot;total_veterans&quot;]
person = person.merge(veterans.reset_index(), on=[&quot;spmfamunit&quot;])

person[&quot;child_with_vet&quot;] = (person.child) &amp;amp; (person.total_veterans &amp;gt; 0)
person[&quot;child_with_no_vet&quot;] = (person.child) &amp;amp; (person.total_veterans == 0)

# Show total veterans in millions
total_veterans = (person.veteran * person.asecwt).sum()
total_veterans / 1_000_000

# Calculate total AGI
person[&quot;adjginc&quot;].replace({99999999: 0}, inplace=True)
population = person.asecwt.sum()
person[&quot;weighted_agi&quot;] = person.adjginc * person.asecwt
total_agi = person.weighted_agi.sum()

# Calculate AGI tax rate per dollar of UBI
fed_tax_rate_per_dollar_ubi_monthly = (population * 12) / total_agi

# Create table showing tax amounts
tax_rates = pd.DataFrame(np.arange(0, 1001, 50))
tax_rates.columns = [&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;]


def tax(monthly_ubi):
    return (monthly_ubi * fed_tax_rate_per_dollar_ubi_monthly * 100).round(1)


def tax_row(row):
    return tax(row.monthly_ubi)


tax_rates[&quot;tax_rate&quot;] = tax_rates.apply(tax_row, axis=1)
tax_rates.columns = [&quot;Monthly UBI&quot;, &quot;Flat Tax Rate on AGI&quot;]


def ubi(status, monthly_ubi):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;At a given UBI level, calculate the poverty rate, median resources,
    mean resources, and percent of people better off for:
    * Veterans
    * Non-Veterans
    * Children living with Veteran
    * Children not living with Veterans
  
    Args:
        status: A person's Veteran status.
            For this simulation their are 4 categories:
            * Veteran
            * Non-Veteran
            * Child living with a Veteran
            * Children not living with a Veteran
        monthly_ubi: the monthly cash transfer given to each person
  
    Returns:
        pandas Series with four elements for the selected group:
        * Poverty rate
        * Median resources per person
        * Mean resources per person
        * Percent of people better off
    &quot;&quot;&quot;

    # Create a copy of the person DataFrame
    target_persons = person.copy(deep=True)

    # Calculate a person's tax increase
    target_persons[&quot;tax_increase&quot;] = (
        fed_tax_rate_per_dollar_ubi_monthly * monthly_ubi * target_persons.adjginc
    )

    # Calculate the total UBI per SPM unit.
    target_persons[&quot;total_ubi&quot;] = target_persons.spmnpers * 12 * monthly_ubi

    # Calculate the total tax increase of an SPM unit
    spmu = target_persons.groupby([&quot;spmfamunit&quot;])[[&quot;tax_increase&quot;]].sum()
    spmu.columns = [&quot;total_tax_increase&quot;]
    target_persons = target_persons.merge(
        spmu, left_on=[&quot;spmfamunit&quot;], right_index=True
    )

    # Calculate each SPM unit's tax rate person
    target_persons[&quot;new_spm_resources&quot;] = (
        target_persons.spmtotres
        + target_persons.total_ubi
        - target_persons.total_tax_increase
    )

    # Calculate the new resources per person of each SPM unit
    target_persons[&quot;new_resources_per_person&quot;] = (
        target_persons.new_spm_resources / target_persons.spmnpers
    )

    # Slice the data based on Race input
    if status == &quot;veteran&quot;:
        target_persons = target_persons[target_persons.veteran]
    if status == &quot;non_veteran&quot;:
        target_persons = target_persons[target_persons.non_veteran]

    if status == &quot;veteran_child&quot;:
        target_persons = target_persons[target_persons.child_with_vet]
    if status == &quot;non_veteran_child&quot;:
        target_persons = target_persons[target_persons.child_with_no_vet]

    # Calculate the change in poverty rate
    target_persons[&quot;poor&quot;] = target_persons.new_spm_resources &amp;lt; target_persons.spmthresh
    total_poor = (target_persons.poor * target_persons.asecwt).sum()
    target_pop = target_persons.asecwt.sum()

    # Calculate percent better off
    target_persons[&quot;better_off&quot;] = (
        target_persons.new_spm_resources &amp;gt; target_persons.spmtotres
    )
    total_better_off = (target_persons.better_off * target_persons.asecwt).sum()
    percent = total_better_off / target_pop * 100

    return pd.Series(
        [
            mdf.weighted_median(
                target_persons, &quot;new_resources_per_person&quot;, &quot;asecwt&quot;
            ).round(0),
            mdf.weighted_mean(
                target_persons, &quot;new_resources_per_person&quot;, &quot;asecwt&quot;
            ).round(0),
            (total_poor / target_pop * 100).round(1),
            percent,
        ]
    )


def ubi_row(row):
    &quot;&quot;&quot; run the ubi function across the rows of a DataFrame.
  
    Arguments
    row: the row of the DataFrame containing a person's race and the monthly UBI amount
  
    Returns
    The poverty rate for the selected row.
    The median resources per person for the selected row.
    The mean resources per person for the selected row.
    The percent of people better off under the program for the selected row.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    return ubi(row.status, row.monthly_ubi)


# Create a DataFrame that has each the each monthly UBI amount for each race input
summary = mdf.cartesian_product(
    {
        &quot;monthly_ubi&quot;: np.arange(0, 1001, 50),
        &quot;status&quot;: [&quot;veteran&quot;, &quot;non_veteran&quot;, &quot;veteran_child&quot;, &quot;non_veteran_child&quot;],
    }
)

# Calculate the poverty rate for each row of the summary DataFrame
summary[
    [
        &quot;med_resources_per_person&quot;,
        &quot;mean_resources_per_person&quot;,
        &quot;poverty_rate&quot;,
        &quot;better_off&quot;,
    ]
] = summary.apply(ubi_row, axis=1)

summary2 = summary[summary[&quot;status&quot;] != &quot;non_veteran_child&quot;]
summary2 = summary2[summary2[&quot;status&quot;] != &quot;veteran_child&quot;]
# Format text
center = {
    &quot;med_resources_per_person&quot;: &quot;Median resources&quot;,
    &quot;mean_resources_per_person&quot;: &quot;Mean resources&quot;,
}
status = {
    &quot;veteran&quot;: &quot;Veterans&quot;,
    &quot;non_veteran&quot;: &quot;Non-Veteran adults&quot;,
    &quot;veteran_child&quot;: &quot;Children in Veteran households&quot;,
    &quot;non_veteran_child&quot;: &quot;Children in non-Veteran households&quot;,
}

summary[&quot;status&quot;] = summary[&quot;status&quot;].map(status)
summary2[&quot;status&quot;] = summary2[&quot;status&quot;].map(status)

# Colors from https://material.io/design/color/the-color-system.html
BLUE = &quot;#1976D2&quot;
DARK_BLUE = &quot;#0D47A1&quot;
BARELY_BLUE = &quot;#64B5F6&quot;
GRAY = &quot;#9E9E9E&quot;
LIGHT_GRAY = &quot;#E0E0E0&quot;

COLOR_MAP = {
    &quot;Veterans&quot;: BLUE,
    &quot;Non-Veteran adults&quot;: GRAY,
    &quot;Children in Veteran households&quot;: BARELY_BLUE,
    &quot;Children in non-Veteran households&quot;: LIGHT_GRAY,
}


def line_graph(df, x, y, color, title, xaxis_title, yaxis_title):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Style for line graphs.
    
    Args:
        df: DataFrame with data to be plotted.
        x: The string representing the column in df that holds the new
            spending in billions.
        y: The string representing the column in df that holds the poverty
            rate.
        color: The string representing the UBI type.
        xaxis_title: The string represnting the xaxis-title.
        yaxis_title: The string representing the yaxis-title.
    
    Returns:
        Nothing. Shows the plot.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    fig = px.line(df, x=x, y=y, color=color, color_discrete_map=COLOR_MAP)
    fig.update_layout(
        title=title,
        xaxis_title=xaxis_title,
        yaxis_title=yaxis_title,
        yaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;%&quot;,
        font=dict(family=&quot;Roboto&quot;),
        hovermode=&quot;x&quot;,
        xaxis_tickprefix=&quot;$&quot;,
        xaxis_ticksuffix=&quot;&quot;,
        plot_bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;,
        legend_title_text=&quot;&quot;,
    )
    fig.update_traces(mode=&quot;markers+lines&quot;, hovertemplate=None)

    hide_line = [&quot;Children in Veteran households&quot;, &quot;Children in non-Veteran households&quot;]

    fig.for_each_trace(
        lambda trace: trace.update(visible=&quot;legendonly&quot;)
        if trace.name in hide_line
        else ()
    )

    return fig


fig = line_graph(
    df=summary,
    x=&quot;monthly_ubi&quot;,
    y=&quot;poverty_rate&quot;,
    color=&quot;status&quot;,
    title=&quot;The impact of a UBI on Veterans and their families&quot;,
    xaxis_title=&quot;Monthly UBI&quot;,
    yaxis_title=&quot;SPM poverty rate&quot;,
)
fig.show()
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/veterans/2020-11-11-veterans-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies suggest that reducing Veteran poverty could address issues disproportionately experienced by Veterans. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hud.gov/press/press_releases_media_advisories/HUD_No_19_163&quot;&gt;Over 37,000 Veterans&lt;/a&gt; experience homelessness on a given night, and a recent experiment in Canada found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://forsocialchange.org/our-story&quot;&gt;cash transfers accelerated&lt;/a&gt; transitions out of homelessness. Veterans have a higher rate of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4638236/&quot;&gt;mental illness&lt;/a&gt;, especially depression, PTSD, and substance abuse disorder, while Finland’s UBI experiment &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheUBICenter/status/1258064957406511104&quot;&gt;improved mental health&lt;/a&gt;. Controlling for age and sex, the Veteran suicide rate exceeds the non-Veteran suicide rate by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mentalhealth.va.gov/docs/data-sheets/2019/2019_National_Veteran_Suicide_Prevention_Annual_Report_508.pdf&quot;&gt;50 percent&lt;/a&gt;, and a review of cash transfer programs in low- and middle-income countries found &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbrg.bsg.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/2020-05/the_role_of_cash_transfers_in_preventing_suicides_in_lmics_1.pdf&quot;&gt;significant suicide reductions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unique Veteran experience warrants investment in tailored solutions, such as the health and education programs offered by the VA. Cash transfers like universal basic income can also reduce their incidence of poverty and empower them to meet their individual needs. Even modest basic incomes such as a tax-funded $300 per month would halve Veteran poverty and more than halve poverty among children of Veterans, improving poverty-linked outcomes for those who have served.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;max&quot;, &quot;nate&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="veterans" />
      
        <category term="poverty" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Unconditional cash would fill in gaps of VA programs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">One in five Americans with disabilities is in poverty. Even small basic incomes would help.</title>
      <link href="/ada30" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One in five Americans with disabilities is in poverty. Even small basic incomes would help." />
      <published>2020-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/ada30</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/ada30">&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.plot.ly/plotly-latest.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.5.1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Americans with Disabilities Act reaches its 30th anniversary, we wanted to look beyond the workplace to poverty, safety net programs, and basic income. Today, more than 1 in 5 Americans with disabilities live below the poverty threshold, nearly twice the rate of Americans without disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While America provides some income support to its citizens with disabilities through Supplemental Security Income (SSI) and Social Security Disability Insurance (SSDI), these programs inevitably leave many out.  Today, 22% of households with people with disabilities do not receive any federal government assistance.  Further, just 14% of households of families where someone is disabled collected SSI, a program “designed to help aged, blind, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ssa.gov/ssi/&quot;&gt;disabled people&lt;/a&gt;, who have little or no income.”  Unemployment insurance was the only program in our analysis that was more likely to go to families without people with disabilities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
### LOAD PACKAGES ####

import pandas as pd
import plotly.express as px
import microdf as mdf
import numpy as np

### COLORS ###

# Colors from https://material.io/design/color/the-color-system.html
BLUE = '#1976D2'
DARK_BLUE = '#0D47A1'
BARELY_BLUE = '#E3F2FD'
GRAY = '#BDBDBD'


### LOAD DATA ###

person_raw = pd.read_csv('https://github.com/MaxGhenis/datarepo/raw/master/pppub19.csv.gz',
                         usecols=['MARSUPWT', 'SPM_ID', 'SPM_RESOURCES',
                                  'SPM_POVTHRESHOLD', 'A_AGE', 'PEDISDRS',
                                  'PEDISEAR', 'PEDISEYE', 'PEDISOUT',
                                  'PEDISPHY', 'PEDISREM', 'SPM_NUMPER',
                                  'SS_VAL', 'SSI_VAL', 'SPM_SNAPSUB',
                                  'PAW_TYP', 'SPM_CAPHOUSESUB', 'UC_VAL'])

### PREPROCESS ###

person = person_raw.copy(deep = True)
person.columns = person.columns.str.lower()
person['weight'] = person.marsupwt / 100
# Create a new dataframe that only includes adults.
adults = person[person['a_age'] &amp;gt; 17].copy(deep=True)

# Create a column that shows if people have any disabilities.
adults['any_disability'] = ((adults.pedisdrs == 1) | 
                            (adults.pedisear == 1) | 
                            (adults.pediseye == 1) |
                            (adults.pedisout == 1) | 
                            (adults.pedisphy == 1) |
                            (adults.pedisrem == 1))

# Map the ASEC codes to disability types.
PWD_MAP = ({'pedisdrs': 'Self-care',
            'pedisear': 'Hearing',
            'pediseye': 'Vision',
            'pedisout': 'Mobility',
            'pedisphy': 'Physical',
            'pedisrem': 'Cognitive',
            'any_disability': 'Any'
           })

# group individual questions by spm group
adults['got_tanf'] = np.where(adults.paw_typ == 1, 1, 0)
PERSON_SPM_COLS = ['ss_val', 'ssi_val', 'uc_val', 'got_tanf']
groups = adults.groupby('spm_id')[PERSON_SPM_COLS].sum()
groups.columns = ['spm_' + i for i in PERSON_SPM_COLS]
adults2 = adults.merge(groups, left_on='spm_id', right_index=True)
# Also look into OI_OFF column: Value 3 = AFDC

# All PWD records.
adults_pwd = adults2[adults2.any_disability]

# Note these columns don't represent anything consistent
# except that &amp;gt;0 values indicate that the SPM unit received it.

# create a columns map
BEN_MAP = ({'spm_ss_val': 'Social Security', 
            'spm_ssi_val': 'Supplemental Security Income',
            'spm_got_tanf': 'TANF',
            'spm_uc_val': 'Unemployment',
            'spm_snapsub': 'SNAP',
            'spm_caphousesub': 'Housing Assistance',
            'spm_any_ben': 'Any'
            })

# Sum up all columns except the last (which is any, itself).
adults2['spm_any_ben'] = adults2[list(BEN_MAP.keys())[:-1]].sum(axis=1)


# Create a function that calculates percent of people with disabilities
# receiving each benefit.
def percent_bens(ben_column, has_disability):
    target_adults = adults2[adults2.any_disability == has_disability]
    total_w_ben = ((target_adults[ben_column] &amp;gt; 0) * target_adults.weight)
    return ((total_w_ben.sum() / target_adults.weight.sum()) * 100).round(1)

def percent_bens_row(row):
    return percent_bens(row.ben_column, row.has_disability)

benefits = mdf.cartesian_product({'ben_column': BEN_MAP.keys(),
                                  'has_disability': [True, False]
                                  })

benefits['percentage'] = benefits.apply(percent_bens_row, axis=1)
benefits['benefit'] = benefits.ben_column.map(BEN_MAP)
benefits = (benefits.sort_values(['percentage','benefit'],
                               ascending=(True, True)))
benefits['disability_text'] = np.where(benefits.has_disability,
                                       'Has disability', 'No disability')

fig = px.bar(benefits, x='percentage', y='benefit', color='disability_text',
             labels={'percentage': 'Percent receiving benefit',
                      'benefit': 'Benefit'},
             title='Share of Americans in families receiving benefits',
             text='percentage',
             orientation='h',
             barmode='group',
             color_discrete_map={'Has disability': BLUE, 'No disability': GRAY}
)

fig.update_layout(barmode='group',
                  font=dict(family='Roboto'),
                  plot_bgcolor='white',
                  yaxis_title='',
                  legend_title='',
                  xaxis_ticksuffix='%',
                  legend={'traceorder': 'reversed'}
                 )

fig.update_traces(texttemplate='%{text}%')

fig.show(config={'displayModeBar': False})
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/ada30/2020-07-31-ada30-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universal payments would ensure that all households receive government assistance.  The remainder of this paper examines how universal payments can alleviate poverty for Americans with disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conduct this analysis, we used the most recent Current Population Survey March Supplement, which reflects 2018 income.  Using this data, we simulated how various UBI levels impact the poverty rate of Americans with a variety of disabilities. For reference, the chart below shows the amount of Americans identifying with each type of disability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
# data for bar graph that shows amount of people with each disability

total_cognitive_m = (adults.weight * (adults.pedisrem==1)).sum()/1e6
total_mobility_m = (adults.weight * (adults.pedisout==1)).sum()/1e6
total_self_care_m = (adults.weight * (adults.pedisdrs==1)).sum()/1e6
total_physical_m = (adults.weight * (adults.pedisphy==1)).sum()/1e6 
total_vision_m = (adults.weight * (adults.pediseye==1)).sum()/1e6
total_hearing_m = (adults.weight* (adults.pedisear==1)).sum()/1e6
total_pwd_m = (adults.weight * adults.any_disability).sum()/1e6
total_pwd = (adults.weight * adults.any_disability).sum()

total_dict = {'disability_type': ['Cognitive', 'Mobility', 'Self-care', 'Physical',
                       'Vision', 'Hearing', 'Any'],
              'total_millions': [total_cognitive_m, total_mobility_m, total_self_care_m, 
                        total_physical_m, total_vision_m, total_hearing_m,
                        total_pwd_m] 
}

total_df = pd.DataFrame(total_dict)
total_df = total_df.round(1)
total_df = (total_df.sort_values(['total_millions','disability_type'],
                               ascending=(False, True)))

fig = px.bar(total_df, x = 'total_millions', y='disability_type',
             title='Number of adults reporting each disability type',
             color='disability_type',
             text='total_millions',
             orientation = 'h',
             color_discrete_map={'Cognitive': BLUE,
                                 'Mobility': BLUE,
                                 'Self-care': BLUE,
                                 'Physical': BLUE,
                                 'Vision': BLUE,
                                 'Hearing': BLUE,
                                 'Any': DARK_BLUE})

fig.update_layout(showlegend=False,
                  xaxis_ticksuffix='M',
                  font=dict(family='Roboto'),
                  plot_bgcolor='white',
                  xaxis_title='',
                  yaxis_title=''
                 )
fig.update_traces(texttemplate='%{text}M')

fig.show(config={'displayModeBar': False})
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/ada30/2020-07-31-ada30-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;findings&quot;&gt;Findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that  a UBI has the potential to drastically reduce poverty among adults with disabilities and that a $300 monthly UBI would cut the poverty rate in half, from 20.7 percent to 9.2 percent.  A UBI of $1,000 per month, such as in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubicenter.org/plans&quot;&gt;Andrew Yang’s Freedom Dividend&lt;/a&gt;, would shrink the poverty rate among people with disabilities to 1.3 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the status quo, poverty rates are highest among people with cognitive, physical, and self-care disabilities, which all exceed 24 percent.  A UBI of $500 per month would slash all these rates below 7 percent, a third of their current level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interactive chart below shows the poverty rate for each group with various monthly UBI levels up to $1,000 at $100 intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button3&quot; onclick=&quot;f3()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_3&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
# Determine the poverty rate impact for Americans with disabilities of a UBI from $0 per month to $1000 per month

def pwd_pov(type_of_disability, monthly_ubi=0):
    target_persons = adults[adults[type_of_disability]==1].copy(deep=True)
    target_persons['total_ubi'] = person.spm_numper * monthly_ubi * 12
    target_persons['new_spm_resources'] = (target_persons.total_ubi
                                           + target_persons.spm_resources)
    target_persons['poor'] = (target_persons.new_spm_resources 
                              &amp;lt; target_persons.spm_povthreshold)
    population_target = target_persons.weight.sum()
    total_target_poor = (target_persons.poor * target_persons.weight).sum()
    total_pov_rate = total_target_poor / population_target

    return (total_pov_rate * 100).round(1)

def pwd_pov_row(row):
    return pwd_pov(row.type_of_disability, row.monthly_ubi)

# Create a dataframe that summarizes the outputs of the function

summary = mdf.cartesian_product({'type_of_disability':PWD_MAP,
                       'monthly_ubi': np.arange(0,1001,100)})

summary['poverty_rate'] = summary.apply(pwd_pov_row, axis=1)
summary['disability_type'] = summary.type_of_disability.map(PWD_MAP)
summary = (summary.sort_values(['poverty_rate','disability_type'],
                               ascending=(False, True)))

# Add new rows for the difference between original and current (w/UBI) pov.
original_pov = summary[summary.monthly_ubi == 0].copy(deep=True)
original_pov.drop(['monthly_ubi', 'disability_type'], axis=1, inplace=True)
original_pov.rename(columns = {'poverty_rate': 'original_poverty_rate'},
                    inplace=True)
summary = summary.merge(original_pov, on='type_of_disability')

# Calculate the difference
summary['poverty_delta'] = (summary.original_poverty_rate -
                            summary.poverty_rate).round(1)

SUM_MAP = ({'poverty_rate': 'People in poverty',
            'poverty_delta': 'People no longer in poverty'})

summary_long = summary.melt(id_vars=['disability_type', 'monthly_ubi',
                                     'original_poverty_rate'],
                            value_vars=['poverty_rate', 'poverty_delta'])
summary_long['poverty_in_out'] = summary_long.variable.map(SUM_MAP)
summary_long.sort_values(['original_poverty_rate', 'monthly_ubi'],
                         ascending=[True, True], inplace=True)

fig = px.bar(summary_long, x='value', y='disability_type',
             color='poverty_in_out',
             animation_frame='monthly_ubi', range_x=[0,25],
             labels={&quot;value&quot;: &quot;SPM poverty rate&quot;,
                     &quot;disability_type&quot;: &quot;Disability type&quot;,
                     &quot;monthly_ubi&quot;: &quot;Monthly UBI&quot;
                    },
             title='Effect of UBI on poverty among adults with disabilities',
             orientation='h',
             color_discrete_map={'People in poverty': BLUE,
                                 'People no longer in poverty': BARELY_BLUE
                                }
             )

fig.update_layout(xaxis_ticksuffix='%',
                  plot_bgcolor='white',
                  font=dict(family='Roboto'),
                  legend_title_text=''
                 )

fig.show(config={'displayModeBar': False})
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f3() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_3&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button3&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset3&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/ada30/2020-07-31-ada30-asset-3.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset3&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research fits a growing trend, that stripping benefits of their bureaucracy, and making payments truly universal, is often the simplest way to reach target groups.  Programs that impose administrative burdens will continue to miss many Americans with disabilities, while a UBI will not.  Still, it is important to acknowledge that cash transfers alone are not sufficient in protecting the rights of Americans with disabilities and that  we should follow disability rights advocates in the fight for equal access to healthcare, transportation, independent living, and more workplace portections.   But reducing poverty among people with disabilities is a worthy goal of its own, and our analysis shows that a UBI would be a powerful tool in accomplishing that aim.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;nate&quot;, &quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="disability" />
      
        <category term="poverty" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">$300 per month would cut the rate to one in ten.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Basic income plans from congressional candidates Mike Broihier and Suraj Patel</title>
      <link href="/basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic income plans from congressional candidates Mike Broihier and Suraj Patel" />
      <published>2020-06-23T18:53:56+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-23T18:53:56+00:00</updated>
      <id>/basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel">&lt;p&gt;Of the Democrats in &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/todays-elections-in-kentucky-and-new-york-are-high-stakes-for-the-progressive-movement/&quot;&gt;six states&lt;/a&gt; voting in primaries or primary run-offs today, some will see basic-income-friendly candidates on their ballot. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mikeforky.com/&quot;&gt;Mike Broihier&lt;/a&gt; is one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/United_States_Senate_election_in_Kentucky,_2020&quot;&gt;ten candidates&lt;/a&gt; running for the chance to battle Senate Majority Leader Mitch McConnell in Kentucky, while &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.surajpatel.nyc/&quot;&gt;Suraj Patel&lt;/a&gt; is one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/New_York%27s_12th_Congressional_District&quot;&gt;three challengers&lt;/a&gt; to incumbent Carolyn Maloney in New York’s 12th congressional district (a blue district in New York City).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broihier is a farmer and former Marine who’s earned the endorsement of former presidential candidate Andrew Yang by making UBI the centerpiece of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://mikeforky.com/issues/&quot;&gt;economic plan&lt;/a&gt;. Patel is an attorney and business ethics lecturer who has called for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.surajpatel.nyc/new-page&quot;&gt;child allowance&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@surajpatelnyc/fiscal-response-to-covid-19-6a4384e5e89f&quot;&gt;emergency UBI&lt;/a&gt; throughout the Covid-19 economic crisis. Here’s more on their basic income plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;both-support-emergency-ubi&quot;&gt;Both support emergency UBI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broihier and Patel join many prominent economists in calling for emergency relief payments for each person, for each month of the crisis. By avoiding means-testing, these payments could be delivered more quickly and without excluding people whose income has changed in the past couple of years (the duration the means-tested Recovery Rebates considered for determining eligibility). Both also support giving some to children as well as adults, which my research found is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/how-universal-basic-income-can-keep-poverty-from-rising-amid-covid-19-9950e4a58030&quot;&gt;more cost-effective way&lt;/a&gt; to stabilize poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broihier &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kiBlfBFx7UBdgORWqRgKUt8r6EDzVc8LcqB8-072aJU/edit&quot;&gt;proposes&lt;/a&gt; $2,000 per adult and $1,000 per child, “each and every month until this crisis has ended and the economy has been revved back up out of recession.” The US has &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?q=population%20by%20age&amp;amp;hidePreview=false&amp;amp;tid=ACSST1Y2018.S0101&amp;amp;t=Age%20and%20Sex&amp;amp;vintage=2018&quot;&gt;73 million children and 254 million adults&lt;/a&gt;, so this plan would cost $580 billion per month, or about a third of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@surajpatelnyc/fiscal-response-to-covid-19-6a4384e5e89f&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; is half that of Broihier’s: $1,000 per adult and $500 per child, “until the pandemic is contained and the Sahm Rule is no longer triggered.” The Sahm Rule, named after economist Claudia Sahm (who also supports direct payments), identifies recessions as periods when the three-month moving average of the unemployment rate is 0.5 percentage points above its low from the prior 12 months. This would cost $290 billion per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As captured in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://covid19tracker.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;Covid-19 tracker&lt;/a&gt;, several other members of Congress support cash payments to relieve economic stresses from our historic recession, and some have introduced legislation to provide them. Some of these proposals have been universal and not monthly, such as Senator Mitt Romney’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.romney.senate.gov/romney-calls-urgent-action-additional-coronavirus-response-measures&quot;&gt;call&lt;/a&gt; for one-time $1,000 payments to each adult. Others have been monthly but not universal, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://static.politico.com/ea/52/4e9d51534400b64f3a5fa40aabfd/gai20332-4.pdf&quot;&gt;Monthly Economic Crisis and Support Act&lt;/a&gt; from Senators Harris, Sanders, and Markey, which provides payments of $2,000 per person per month, phasing out for high-income households. However, universal monthly payments have been proposed by Senator &lt;a href=&quot;https://berniesanders.com/issues/emergency-response-coronavirus-pandemic/&quot;&gt;Bernie Sanders&lt;/a&gt; and Representatives &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/justinamash/status/1242486422180855815&quot;&gt;Justin Amash&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/6553&quot;&gt;Rashida Tlaib&lt;/a&gt; (and 11 cosponsors), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/6290/cosponsors?searchResultViewType=expanded&quot;&gt;Ilhan Omar&lt;/a&gt; (and 4 cosponsors), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-resolution/897&quot;&gt;Tulsi Gabbard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;broihiers-ambitious-ubi-is-part-of-wide-ranging-fiscalreform&quot;&gt;Broihier’s ambitious UBI is part of wide-ranging fiscal reform&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Covid-19 crisis ends, Broihier &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kiBlfBFx7UBdgORWqRgKUt8r6EDzVc8LcqB8-072aJU/edit&quot;&gt;proposes&lt;/a&gt; transitioning the emergency UBI into a smaller permanent one: monthly payments of $1,200 per adult and $400 per child. This targets bringing everyone above the official poverty measure, with a buffer to pay new taxes funding the UBI. It would cost $330 billion per month — $4 trillion per year, or about a fifth of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2020-06-23-basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel-1.png#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary funding sources would be a 10 percent value added tax (VAT) and the elimination of all tax deductions and credits, including the standard deduction. A 10 percent VAT would raise about &lt;a href=&quot;https://taxfoundation.org/andrew-yang-value-added-tax-universal-basic-income/&quot;&gt;$1 trillion per year&lt;/a&gt;, and Broihier estimates that eliminating all deductions and credits would raise about $1.5 trillion per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the cost would also be offset by counting the UBI as income against means-tested benefit eligibility, and eliminating Temporary Aid for Needy Families (which now only gives about &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/most-welfare-dollars-dont-go-directly-to-poor-people-anymore/&quot;&gt;a quarter of its funds&lt;/a&gt; as cash).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the deficit impact over time, Broihier proposes taxing public US companies based on their market capitalization: 3 percent upon IPO, merger, or acquisition, and another 0.5 percent per year. The tax would be paid in stock rather than cash, creating a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peoplespolicyproject.org/projects/social-wealth-fund&quot;&gt;social wealth fund&lt;/a&gt; that bears interest for future public spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Broihier proposes eliminating the income cap on payroll taxes, while also lowering rates from 6.2 percent to 4 percent on both employers and employees. Social Security benefits would not change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of the $1,200/$400 UBI, Broihier would institute a carbon fee-and-dividend, where each metric ton of carbon emissions is priced at $40 — rising $15 per year — and the proceeds are shared equally with Americans. As he notes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econstatement.org/&quot;&gt;over 3,300 economists&lt;/a&gt; support the carbon fee-and-dividend model as an effective and equitable climate change tool, including many who have held top government positions. There are also a number of carbon fee-and-dividend bills in Congress, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://energyinnovationact.org/&quot;&gt;Energy Innovation and Carbon Dividend Act&lt;/a&gt;, which has 81 co-sponsors and a similar structure to Broihier’s plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;patels-generous-child-allowance&quot;&gt;Patel’s generous child allowance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2020-06-23-basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel-2.png#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.surajpatel.nyc/new-page&quot;&gt;Family Opportunity Guarantee&lt;/a&gt;, Suraj Patel proposes replacing the Child Tax Credit (CTC) with “a Universal Child Dividend of $500 per kid, per month ages 0–5; $350 per kid, per month ages 6–17.” The Universal Child Dividend would cost about $360 billion per year, or $240 billion after &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pgpf.org/budget-basics/what-is-the-child-tax-credit&quot;&gt;replacing the CTC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patel appears to have modeled this after the American Family Act (AFA), Senator Michael Bennet’s plan to make the CTC fully available to low-income families, increase the amount (with a bonus for young children), and distribute it monthly rather than annually. Specifically, it makes the credit “fully refundable,” meaning the entirety of it is provided to families that don’t owe net federal taxes. As I &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@MaxGhenis/we-should-replace-the-child-tax-credit-with-a-universal-child-benefit-33773de07271&quot;&gt;wrote in 2018&lt;/a&gt;, even a budget-neutral replacement of the Child Tax Credit with a child allowance would cut child poverty by 15 percent, since the CTC’s non-refundable component excludes our poorest kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AFA would boost the up-to-$2,000 CTC to $3,000 per child aged 6 to 16 and $3,600 per child under 6. It’s been estimated to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.povertycenter.columbia.edu/news-internal/2019/3/5/the-afa-and-child-poverty&quot;&gt;cut child poverty by 42 percent&lt;/a&gt;, and is co-sponsored by most Democrats in both the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/senate-bill/690/related-bills&quot;&gt;Senate&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/1560&quot;&gt;House&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Patel claims, “The Universal Child Dividend alone will slash child poverty in half,” which seems like a conservative estimate given the payments would be about 50 percent larger than the AFA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;these-plans-would-be-progressive&quot;&gt;These plans would be progressive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In lieu of a full distributional analysis, we can learn from other analyses of similar plans. For example, my analysis of Andrew Yang’s Freedom Dividend found that it would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/distributional-analysis-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-d8dab818bf1b&quot;&gt;highly progressive&lt;/a&gt;, despite the slightly regressive VAT structure and reduction of benefit outlays. Other analyses have found that child allowances &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5743308460b5e922a25a6dc7/t/5c7fe48b1905f46e1214bc42/1551885452114/Poverty+%26+Social+Policy+Brief+3_3.pdf&quot;&gt;cut poverty substantially&lt;/a&gt; — even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peoplespolicyproject.org/2018/11/29/a-child-allowance-would-be-very-effective-at-poverty-reduction/&quot;&gt;more than adult UBIs&lt;/a&gt; per dollar spent. Broihier’s addition of a child allowance to Yang’s adult-only proposal, and Patel’s Universal Child Dividend, are both effective antipoverty policies that would also invest in our future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Max Ghenis</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="us" />
      
        <category term="elections" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The two advocates of emergency UBI are running in Democratic primaries today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
